<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The husbandlye ordring and gouernmente of poultrie Practised by the learnedste, and suche as haue bene knowne skilfullest in that arte, and in our tyme.</title>
            <author>Mascall, Leonard, d. 1589.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1581</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 171 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 82 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07184</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17589</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107290</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842992</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842992</idno>
            <idno type="VID">7695</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07184)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7695)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 713:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The husbandlye ordring and gouernmente of poultrie Practised by the learnedste, and suche as haue bene knowne skilfullest in that arte, and in our tyme.</title>
                  <author>Mascall, Leonard, d. 1589.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[160] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Thomas Purfoote, for Gerarde Dewse,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1581.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: L.M. [i.e. Leonard Mascall].</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The nourishing and gouernmente of poultrie.</note>
                  <note>With an index.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ B-K L⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Poultry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:7695:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7695:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>¶ The Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandlye ordring and <hi>Gouernmente of</hi> Poultrie.</p>
            <p>Practiſed by the Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedſte, and ſuche as haue bene knowne skilfulleſt in that Arte, and in our tyme.</p>
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London, by Thomas Purfoote, for <hi>Gerards Dewſe. 1581.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:7695:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7695:2"/>
            <head>To Miſtriſſe Katherine VVoodford (vvife to maiſter Iames Woodforde Eſquier) and cheefe Clarke of the Kitching to the Queenes Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie Leonarde Maſtall vvisheth a proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous eſtate in health long to continue.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>braunce of your VVorſhipfull Parentes, gentle miſtriſſe VVood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forde, vnto whome my father &amp; his family haue alwayes borne good vvill, and you ſhewing likewiſe a continuall courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie towards me and them, perceiuing alſo youre vviſe and orderlye vſing your houſe for your familie &amp; houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdes vvith a deſired minde to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ſame in knowledge, howe to vſe and gouern Poultrie to profit for maintenance of your ſaid houſekee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, which thing you haue bene de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to know, vvith the ordring of ſtraunge vvildfoule, how to preſerue and keepe them to pleaſure and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite.
<pb facs="tcp:7695:3"/>I hauing known your parents (in Breſtall) and you from my youth, ſhewing herein my good wil towards you and your fathers houſe, to far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and pleaſure your deſired minde therein, the remembraunce thereof hath moued me at this preſent to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſe and tranſlate out of Frenche Columella and Stephanus into En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh, certaine orders for gouernment of the ſayd poultrie, and alſo the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring of diuers other vvildfoule, bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides manye other approued collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons &amp; practiſes learned in this realm, neceſſary to bee knowne to all good houſholders, deſiring you to bee the patrone and defender hereof in print, in ſo doing I ſhall thinke my trauaile vvell beſtowed, and my time vvell ſpent. Thus I leaue, vvishing you a proſperous eſtate, vvith increaſe of vvorship long to continue to the ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of God.</p>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:7695:3"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or ſo much gentle Reader, as beaſts and Cattaile is profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to mans liuing, ſo is alſo poultrie and other foule a good thing for the common wealth, and ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to them that are houſekeepers, as well for the Gentleman, as the huſbande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and to farther the mayntainaunce of the ſame, I haue taken ſome paynes ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, which here thou ſhalt finde gentle rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, as well for the wilde foule as others, ſuch order for the gouernment thereof, as hath not here before bene written, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealde in our engliſh tongue, with a redy table by Alphabet, to find out any thing herein contayned.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>by L.M. 1581.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="argument">
            <pb facs="tcp:7695:4"/>
            <head>¶ The Argument.</head>
            <p>THe gouernemente of Poultrie is cheefe thing to be maintained fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the ſtate and keeping of a houſe, which thing in reſpect, al mens houſes ough<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to haue, ſpeciallye the Huſbandmanne who ought to haue vnderſtanding her in, how to rule and gouern the ſame a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout his houſe, in which they ought t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be carefull from time to time, as vve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> how to ſaue them as, to breede them, a hereafter ſhall more plainelye appeare Taken forth of <hi>Columella</hi> and <hi>Stephanus</hi> in frenche, vvith diuers other approoued pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:7695:4"/>
            <head>The nourishing and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of Poultrie.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The Order of Columella for the hennehouſe. <hi>Cap. 1.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FYrſt it ſhall bee good to make and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare you a henhouſe to ſaue and keepe your poultrye in, and ſo to ſet it if ye can at the eaſt end of your houſe, made cloſe, &amp; to cloſed beneth with ſtone, or other wayes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ade ſtrong, that no vermyne may breake <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to them by night: made wyth perch and neaſtes within for them to lay and ſitte in when breeding time ſhall bee: or at other times to laye in, and to place your hennes aboue from your other poultry, and your Duckes and Geeſe beneath, each by them ſelues, that they may not fight one with another, for they will not ſo well loue the houſe, but laye and ſitte in corners, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>edges and out places abroad, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they are often kilde.</p>
               <p>Againe ye ſhal make the like neſtes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath for your duckes and geeſe, as aboue for your hennes, and your duckes placed
<pb facs="tcp:7695:5"/>by themſelfe, and your Geeſe themſelue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and to ſee that your henhouſe bee cloſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> thed round about aboue, for feare of Kn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues by night, and other daungers, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that ye make places for them all abou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the ſides of the henhouſe to ſit, and to lay in, with ſeparations eche by himſelfe, all ye ſhall vſe to feede them before the he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> houſe doore morninges and eueninges whiche will cauſe the yong poullets th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> better to loue the hennehouſe, and to v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> them ſo nightlye, will cauſe them and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> olde hennes to ſeeke no other place to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> or rooſte in. Thus much of <hi>Colu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mella</hi> for the henne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:7695:5"/>
               <head>¶ Stephanus Opinion. <hi>Cap. 2.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Our Henne houſe ought to be built on the orient or eaſt part of your houſe, by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>me ſmoke houſe or kitchin, that y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſmoke (whiche is very good for poultry) may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>me vnto them. And your henne houſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> be made of one length and one roome of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eyght, turning towardes the oryent or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſt part of the houſe, and ye ſhall make o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the ſide or end, one narrow entring <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or them to laye, &amp; come to rooſt at night, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſhall alſo make a pertitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aboue for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ennes to ſitte, with perches thereon, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ette very hye from that floure, &amp; placed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne perche a foote from another, and alſo halfe a foote one perch aboue another, and ſet ſo wide as they may be vii foote ſquare within the perches, and on the middeſt ye ſhall make two entryes, one on the right ſide, &amp; another on the left ſide, which ſhall be good to goe and come to the other two <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>houſes. This entres ſhall be made at the endes ioyning to the walles, whiche is to be made eache againſt other in comming into the houſe, againſt which wall ſhalbe made ſuch moderate fire, in ſuch ſort their entring be not let, and alſo looke that the
<pb facs="tcp:7695:6"/>ſmoke do not annoy y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other houſe of your fowle, the roome for your hennes to ſit &amp; lay in, muſt be ſette vii. foote high, and to bee made as large as halfe the height or more.</p>
               <p>Alſo ye ſhall make in eache ſeparation, a ſmall window againſt the eaſt fide of your houſe, that the poultry maye ſee daye to come forth amornings into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> court to feed, and lykewiſe ye muſt haue a care to ſhut the dore of their entring when they bee come in to rooſte at night, to be the more aſſured of them, and to leaue thoſe wyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes open, which are made with lathes, ſo made that no vermine may come in to deuoure the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by night, for they muſt haue ſome cleare light to ſee the better when they go to rooſt, and thoſe perſons that do keepe them, ought to ſee ſpecially to thoſe that do ſitte, and ready to hatche, or haue new hached, for elſe there will be ſoone ſome loſſe of them. Your Separations within, ought to be made cloſe and ſtrong: that one do not trouble another of them that do ſitte, or hatche their young. Some do take it to be a very good waye to ſticke poles before in dyuers places of your hen houſe walles, and thereon to hang panny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
<pb facs="tcp:7695:6"/>or baſkets for your hennes to laye &amp; breed in. Alſo ye muſt put in each neſt a neſt egge, which will cauſe the hennes to laye therin the ſooner: &amp; ye muſt ſo place your perches acroſſe, that your hennes may come and flye eaſily vnto their neſts from tyme to tyme, and ye muſte alwayes ſee that your henhouſe be kept cleane: for when it lyeth foule, it will cauſe the poul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ry to forſake the houſe, &amp; to ſeeke abroad ſome other cleaner place to rooſt in: for it it not good for them to rooſt where muche of their dung is, becauſe it will cleaue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their feete, whiche will cauſe them to haue the goute in their feet, for this cauſe they cutte theyr perches ſquare for them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> rooſt on, for if they be round they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot ſo well ſit thereon. Theſe perches be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made ſquare, they make two holes in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he walles of each ſide of the henne houſe, and puts the perches therein, ſo that they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e not in height from the floure two foot, and the one to bee ſet as farre from the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſo that the poultrye ſhall not ſtryue one with the other for theyr places: and after this ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rte is the beſt waye to make a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heune houſe for your poultry to rooſte in.
<pb facs="tcp:7695:7"/>Alſo ye ſhall make ſome place in theyre corte, to haue alwaies redy water for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, when they haue ſedde. It is not good to haue water for them but in one place, to drinke in, and that the water be kept al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies cleane: for if the water be foule and ſalt, it wil make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue the rye or rume, and it will increaſe alſo the pippe on their tungs. Therefore ye muſt not keepe them from water, whiche water would be ſette in veſſels after this manner. Some pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare troughes of leade to put their water &amp; meat in: but it is moſt certain, thoſe that are made of wood or burnt earth, are moſt wholeſome and beſt for them, the whiche veſſels (for water) ought to bee couered aboue, the one halfe of the veſſell whereas the water is, &amp; therein to haue holes halfe a foote aſunder, wherein the poultry may put their heads &amp; drinke when they haue eaten: for if ye couer not their water, they will ſone marre it with theyr feet. Some do make veſſels with holes in the couer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue, whiche waye is not ſo good: for the poultry when they are aboue theron, they will dung into it, whiche will defile and marre theyr water. And ſee that no lathes
<pb facs="tcp:7695:7"/>or holes be broken, and that theyr perches be ſtraight and euen ſet for them to ſit on. Alſo in ſome places aſſoone as the poultry is gone forth in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> morning, they do clenſe the henhouſe once or twyſe aweeke, and puts theire dung aparte for to helpe the garden, and alſo medowes, &amp; theyr pennes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> neſts muſt be often refreſhed with cleane ſtrawe, and the henne houſe windowes or dore ought to bee ſhut vppe aſſoone as the ſunne is downe, and opened againe in the morning with the riſing of the ſun. Their troughes alſo in winter twiſe a day to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lenſed, &amp; thriſe a day in ſommer, ſo that alwayes theire water maye be freſhe and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>leane. It ſhall be good alſo to caſte ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eſh ſtraw often beſide the Dunghill, and alſo before the henhouſe, whereas the pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets do vſe to ſcrape, and to mixe it with ſome ſand, aſhes, or duſte: to giue them a pleaſure to ſcrape &amp; to baſke them in the ſunne, which they will doo to clenſe their fethers: and looke ye caſt farre from your bouſe your pomes of fruite or wyne when as ye ſtreyne them, for the eating thereof doth coole your hennes, &amp; do let them from laying. Alſo let there be no bright yron
<pb facs="tcp:7695:8"/>ſet vp in the henhouſe: for the brightneſſe thereof will make them to gaze thereat, &amp; ſo feare them, that they will go nye to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the houſe: ye muſt ſee alſo to auoyde the danger of Owles, Cats, Foxes, We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſils, and Polecats, with ſuch lyke, which will nightly deuoure all that they maye come by: and likewyſe on the daye, wyth Buzardes, and Puttockes, Kites, Pyes &amp; Crowes, whiche often deſtroyeth theire egges abroad, and alſo in their henhouſes, if places therin be open: they will alſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure yong Chickens, Duclings, &amp; Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linges vnder theire dammes, or if theire dammes be not nigh them, or for lacke of good tendaunce. Alſo whereas the henne oft times wil depart from hir chickens (&amp; ſodaine loſeth one) as to fly on walles, or pales, or ſuch like: ye ſhal therfore clippe the endes of her great fethers of one of her wings, and not once to ſuffer them to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into your garden, for if they catche once your Garden when they are yong, &amp; by long cuſtome being there brought vp, they will commonly after loue the ſame place where they are ſo brought vp in, &amp; by that meanes ye ſhall haue your Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den
<pb facs="tcp:7695:8"/>ſpilt, &amp; it will hinder them from lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: as for the Cockes and Capons, it is thought good not to ſhorte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or clippe their wings: therefore yee muſt vſe to binde or ſette thornes, or, lay buſhes of thorne on your walles, toppes of pales, or lowe hed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges: or elſe with lath nailde to the toppes of your pale poſtes, and then put thorow your laths pacthred, breſt high of a Cock, from the toppes of your pales, &amp; that will let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from comming in: for the pacthred will hit them on the breſtes, when they would light on the toppe of the pale, and ſo it will put them downe againe. And ſee alſo to other of your poultry, if they vſe to fly or mount on walles or houſes, to cutte their wings for feare of looſing of them, and to vſe for their meate and drinke as is fore mentioned.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Signes in a good Cocke <hi>Cap. 3.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>STephanus</hi> Saith, the ſignes in a good Cocke are theſe: his body large &amp; deepe withall, well and right ireſted, his combe iagged and redde, his eyes round, &amp; great
<pb facs="tcp:7695:9"/>gray or whitiſhe, his byll crooked wyth ſome red and yellow or after an azure co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, his beard or chekes, of the colour of roſes drawing towardes a white and red, his necke fethers faire and long of a gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den colour ſomwhat changing, his legges blacke and well ſtalled, great and ſhorte, his clawes ſhort &amp; ſtrong, his hinder claw wrincled and ſharpe, his taile fayre and ſtraight, great and heauy. Alſo <hi>Columel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la</hi> ſayth, it is not good to keepe a cocke, if he be not ſtout, hot, and knauiſhe, and to be of the ſame coloure as the hennes are, in hauing as many clawes.</p>
               <p>But in his body to be more hier raiſed, his combe to be hye and red as blood, and ſtraight withall, his eyes blacke, or azure colour, his beke ſhort and crooked, with a gray creſt ſhyning like red on white, and all his fethers from the head to the breſt, to be of a changeable colour varying like gold or yellow, his breſt large and bigge, his muſkels on his wings bigge like ones armes, with long wings, his taile faire &amp; long with two rankes of crooked riſing fethers, and to be oft crowing, is a ſigne of a luſty corage, the red colour is thought
<pb facs="tcp:7695:9"/>to be the beſt Cocke, his legges ſhort and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tong, his thyes greate and thicke, and well couered with feathers, and armed well with long ſpurs rough and poynted, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> it is not meete for fighting cocks to be without fayre ſpores, notwithſtanding if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>y doe foewe fayre, ſtrayghte of body, light, fyerce, eager in battayle, vigilante, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>dye, and often trowing, and not eaſily <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>rde: Theſe are the ſignes of a good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ck, for oft times he muſt reſiſt to defend <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> hennes, and to kill Serpentes which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ll bragge agaynſte him, or other vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>us beaſtes, and for theſe Cockes to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e but fiue hennes ſhal be beſt, for theſe Cockes which are ſo hardie to fight with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>er Cockes which treade their hennes, they are hore of nature and ſo laſciuious, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>hough they cannot treade themſelues <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> more, yet they will not ſuffer other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ckes to ſerue their hennes, now for to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ke that heate of iealouſie, ye ſhall ſlitte <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>o peeces of thicke leather, and then put <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>em on his legges, and thoſe wil hang o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>er his fecte which will correct the vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t heat of his iealonzy, which is in him. Thus much here for your Cock.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:7695:10"/>
               <head>¶ The ſignes and properties of a good Henne. <hi>Cap. 4.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe ſignes of a good Henne are theſe to be of a tawnye colour, or of a ruſſet which are counted the cheefeſt coloures and thoſe hennes nexte, which hath y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of their winges blackiſhe, not all blacke but parte: as for the graye &amp; white hens are nothing ſo profitable, the Henne with a tufte of feathers on her head is reaſon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble good, and the low featherde henne al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo: their heads not to be great, and the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> tayles oughte to bee in a meane, and he breſt large, her body deepe and long, f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the greateſt hennes of body are not the a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> teſt hennes to lay, nor yet for that purpo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſo naturall, or if a henne haue v. clawes as the Cocke, they are then more apte t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be troden, and taketh leaſte: as for tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hennes which hath hinder clawes, the will commonly breake their egges in ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thereon, and they ſit not ſo ſurely a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> others, and will oft times eate their egs<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> alſo thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are very fat, or hath the flux<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the bellye, they lay the egge then with oute a ſhell: as for your yong hennes a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7695:10"/>firſt they knowe not how to couer nor go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erne their yong chickens, wherefore it were better to fat the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or put the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to ſome other purpoſe for your profit. As for thoſe hennes whiche doe call or crowe lyke the corke, or doth creke and ſcrape, to help the ſame, ye ſhall pluck of the greateſt fethers of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er wyngs, &amp; giue her of millet wheat to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kte, and alſo of barley, and barley paſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>in ſinale inorſels, &amp; crummes of bread tem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pred in water with ſome barly meale, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ye ſhall keepe her in a cloſe place for a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ye ſhall alſo plucke the fethers of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> head, thies and breſt, and to eate thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in February is the beſt: &amp; for hens <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> fatte, for they will not lay ſo well, wherefore yee ſhall put chalke into their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ter, and mixe alſo their meat therwith, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> at will make them more leane: or tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> their meat with the pouder of bricke, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> it will do the like. If any henne haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> fluxe of the belly, ye ſhall giue her for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> firſt meate, the whites of egges hard <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed, and beaten with two parts of boyld <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſons: and for thoſe hennes which vſe to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ake, &amp; is in a rage with heat, They will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>mmonly hide their eggs, and eate them.
<pb facs="tcp:7695:11"/>Therefore ye muſt vſe to plaiſter an egge ſhell with plaiſter, or paſte vppon pappe, &amp; anoynte it all ouer with the yelke of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther egge, and if ſhe do breake it and find nothing within, ſo ſhe wil at length leaue that vſe. Or lay in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> neſt a peece of chalke like an egge, and it will ſerue as well for that purpoſe, and ye ſhall neuer leaue but a neſt egge in the neſt after ſhe haue layd, alſo when a yong hen do begin to clocke, then ſhe would ſit, if yee will not haue he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fit, put a ſmall pen thorow her noſtrils, for yong hennes are more meeter to laye then to ſit, and the elder hennes are better for to ſit and bring vp yong chickens then to laye. Some do vſe when they would haue a hen to ſit, they rub her all vnder the bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wyth ſtrong nettles, &amp; ſome Farmers wiues are ſo preſiſe, which do wette their bellies in the cold water, to quench they heate, and ſome do vſe to make them faſte from meat foure daies, &amp; ſhuts them vp i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a penne. But then if ye will they ſhall no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſitte, ye muſt within two dayes after tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhe is once coold of her heate, and haue ſo faſted, then put her in the morning vnto the cocke to make her forget her ſitting,
<pb facs="tcp:7695:11"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d ſo ſhe will begin againe to lay. And if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> will haue a Capon to leade your chyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns, it is beſt for to take a great fethered <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pon, and rubbe his belly with nettels as ye do the henne, and if the capon be yong, hee will the better giue hymſelfe to loue the chickens the ſooner, and he will brood and gouerne them as well as the henne: when you take your capon for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe, ye muſt take him towarde nyght, for then it ſhal be beſt, &amp; put the chickens vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> him, if he will not then couer them, net<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e his belly well againe with ſharpe net<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>s, and ſo keepe him in the coope or pen, the ſpace of two or three dayes: or ſo long vntill ye ſee him haue a loue vnto the chic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ When to ſet your hennes. <hi>Cap. 5.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>E ſhall ſette your hens in the increaſe of the Moone from the tenth day to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>teenth is beſt, ſo that they may hatch in the increaſe of the next new Moone. The day in ſieting that doe giue life and forme vnto the chickens are xxi, and of Peacoks,
<pb facs="tcp:7695:12"/>Geeſe, and Duckes, &amp; other water fowle, are nine dayes more. Therefore when ye ſet your egges with other, ye muſte gyue their egges to the henne ten dayes before her owne egges, and then giue her foure egges of hers, or fyue, not aboue, and let them be of the fayreſt and greateſt egges ye can haue, for little egges will bring ſmall chickens. Alſo if the henne be negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent to turne her egges, &amp; do not ſit cloſe or euen on them, it were good ſometymes (when ſhe is gone abroad) gently to turne them, &amp; there be ſome women that thinke it long whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the hen doth ſit, not to let her abide the end of her hatching, but within fourteene days that ſhe haue ſit, ſhe takes forth al the egs one after another, &amp; lokes them in the ſunne beames, and if ſhe can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee no blody ſtreks within, ſhe throws thoſe egges away, and takes others. And likewiſe after the xxi. daye, if ſhe ſee they remayne vncloſed, ſhe takes &amp; rayſes the henne from the neſte, but the good ſitting hen will no more returne to ſit after that ſhe is ſo rayſed and touched.</p>
               <p>Yee may choſe your egges in the ſunne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betwixt your hands, &amp; put them vnder the
<pb facs="tcp:7695:12"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en again, &amp; thoſe egges which ye doubt are not good, and will not hatche in due time thorow the hardnes of the ſhell, yee ſhall bathe them in a veſſell of wood, with luke warme water about the xxviii. daye, and thoſe that doe ſwim aboue, caſte them away, and put the other vnder her again, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>t ye muſt not conſtrayne the hen to riſe from her neſte: when yee do this, alſo ye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aye do great good &amp; ſaue ſome chickens when ye heare them begin to piepe in the ſhell, and cannot come foorth by hardneſſe thereof. Then muſt ye helpe the hen and break the toppe of the ſhell or picke it ſoft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with your finger, although it be the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall office of the henne to do it: ye muſt fulbreak it that the head of the chicke may come foorth, ſo ſhall ye vſe all thoſe that haue hard ſhels, to helpe the henne in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e of hatching.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The time beſt to ſet your yong hens. <hi>Cap. 6.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF ye wyll haue your yong hens &amp; pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> lets to ſit, it ſhall be beſt to ſet them in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e Second yeare of their laying: vntyll
<pb facs="tcp:7695:13"/>the third and fourth yeere: alſo yee maye fette many hennes at one time together, &amp; it ſhall be good afore ye ſet your heune, to lay vnder eache neſte a peece of ſome yron: for as they ſay, it is good againſt thunder to preſerue the chickens: and alſo good a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the breding of the pyppe, or increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of a monſtrous nature in the egges, or to lay of bay leaues about the neſts, is good againſt the thunder, or to put therin the heads of Garlicke, or of grening wede as ſome ſay is good agaynſt the pyppe: or increaſing of monſtrous fruite in the egs, ye may haue of xx eggs, xxi chickens: for ſome egge will haue two yeolkes, &amp; thoſe will bring two chickens.</p>
               <p>They do vſe alſo to ſet the hen in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the Moone, from the ſeconde daye to the fourteenth, (as ſayth <hi>Floren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi>) &amp; <hi>Columella</hi> ſayth, it is good ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting hens fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the tenth vnto the fifteenth, to the end the hennes may hatche and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſe in the increaſe of the next new mone, for there is no more neceſſarye hatching daies for the hen to bring forth chickens, but xxi. and for other water fowle xxviii. vaies: alſo when the henne is gone of her
<pb facs="tcp:7695:13"/>neſt, ye ſhall come and ſearche the bottom of hir neſtes &amp; ſtirre the ſtraw a little, that nothing bee growen or fallen therein to wet and ruſty the neſt: ſome do vſe to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fume the neaſtes with Brimſtone, before they ſet the egges vnder the hen, for they ſay, it will keepe the egges from ill in the ſitting, as often it chaunceth ſome chicke will be dead in the ſhell. Ye ſhall alſo ſet hir with marked egges, to ſee when ſhe hath turned them, ye muſt choſe to ſet the moſt faireſt and neweſt egges of hir owne if ye can poſſibly haue them, and they vſe commonly to ſet their hennes all the ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, from the ſeuenth of February vnto the xxii. of September. As for other times it auaileth little or nothing, much like the firſt ſetting, becauſe the time then is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly cold as a part of winter, &amp; in No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uember, December, &amp; Ianuary nothing auaileth to ſit: In February they vſe to ſet a hen with xv. egges, in March with xix. and in Aprill with xxi. for the moſte greateſt number to ſette is not to be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued aboue xxiii. egges, &amp; from the ſecond of October they vſe to ſet no more, nor they ought not to ſet no more, if they haue
<pb facs="tcp:7695:14"/>not Duens to ſet their Egges in, as they haue at <hi>Malte</hi> and at <hi>Beauceron,</hi> &amp; thoſe Chickens and Pullets are verye euill to bring vp in Winter, and ſo likewiſe the common opinyon of them is, that from mid Iune the Chickens profite but ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, becauſe they do not grow nor increaſe in the heate of Sommer, but very little, if ye will not be to curious (as ſome be) in giuing your henne other egges to ſitte on as well as her owne, as the Gooſe Egge, Pecocke, Turquie and Ducke, if ye ſette theſe with hirs, ye ſhall putte them to the henne ſeuen or nyne dayes before hir own egges: and the common order to ſet egs in number is od, as to ſet ſeuen, nyne, ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and thirteene, &amp;c. whiche is to make them lye rounde in the neaſt, and to haue the odde egge in the middeſt: if ye ſette Fezante egges with your Henne egges, ye neede not doubte to ſette them altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for they aſke all one time to hatche and vnclofe, then if ye will haue them to be Females, take the roundeſt wrincled egges and alſo to haue them all males take the long rough egges, as they ſaye they will be males, alſo ſome doe chuſe
<pb facs="tcp:7695:14"/>the egge wich the hollow croune in the ſide of the coppe for the Females, and alſo the croune in the toppe vnder the ſhell for the males: agayne ſome doe ſaye to haue males, ſette your henne on the maſculyne day in the forenoone, as on Teweſdayes and Thurſedayes, Saturdaye and Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daye: and for the females, ſet your henne in the afternoone on the Feminine dayes as munday and Fryday, and ſome doe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue this ceremonie in ſetting a henne, which is, not to put one Eg after another into the neaſt with her hande, but layes them fyrſt in a wooden platter, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gently puts them altogether in the neaſt, and yee muſt take heede that the Coeke or other hennes doe not ſitte in hir neaſt when ſhe is riſen, for the Cocke with his ſpores wil breake the egges, and the other hennes in ſitting therin, wil make her forſake her neaſte, ye ſhall therefore ſette meate and water by her twiſe a day, that ſhee maye haue no occaſion to riſe &amp; ſeeke her meate, and her egges to coole in the meane tyme, for if a Henne haue greate hunger, and tarrye long in ſeeking her meate, ſome hennes will hardlye returne agayne, if
<pb facs="tcp:7695:15"/>that ſhee bee not of a franke and a free na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>Of Chickens newly hatched. <hi>Cap. 7.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Chickens whiche are newlye hat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched ſhoulde be put into a ſiue and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fumed a little with roſemary, whiche is good to ſaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from the pippe: ye muſt not of two dayes giue them any meate, if one hatche before an other, but keepe them vnder a henne that hath but few, till the reſt be vncloſed, and yet the henne hir ſelf will keepe them tender ynough vnder her winges without hurting, the firſte and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde daye being paſt, ye ſhall take them oute and crum them ſome tender breade, or otemele ſoked in milke, or ſodde wheat, Curdes, or barlye meale, mixte and ſoked in Wine and water, with a fewe Leeke blades hacked ſmall and then a little boi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.</p>
               <p>This order will ſaue them from the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarre, the rye, and the pippe, and from the ſeconde day to the ſixte day, ye ſhall keepe them with the henne in the houſe. Then
<pb facs="tcp:7695:15"/>at the ende of ſixe dayes, ye maye let them goe abroade with the damme, and then giue them of the foreſayde meate, and if ye haue many other ſitting at the ſame time, if they doe hatche, put them vnto a more elder Chickins, and to feede them with the other, or ye m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y putte them to a Capon, and vſe them as is aforeſayde, and then lette the youg hennes be put agayne to the Cocke, but giue not a henne aboue xxv. chickens for to feede, for they cannot be all well couered, alſo ye muſt ſee to the henne that keepes them, that ſhe bee not hote and defirous of the cocke, for then as often as ſhe couers them, ſhe will hurte them and ſcrat them, in putting them ofte in a heat, nor ſhe wil not labour nor ſcrape for their meate, nor yet take regard of the place, that y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> yong may follow hir, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it were better (being ſo hote) not to let her departe the courte, or to put her in ſome penne, or tye her by the legge with ſome ſtring the ſpace of one moneth or ſixe weekes, vntill they bee more ſtronger to guide and helpe themſelues with ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>Alſo there is a cur ioſitie of thoſe perſons
<pb facs="tcp:7695:16"/>which will hatche chickens withoute the henne, which thing may be done, but it is not ſo ſure nor ſo commodyous, whiche is: they ſet the egges an ende in an Ouen, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes of a temperate heate, vpon henne dongue, and they lay bagges of feathers vnder and aboue, and tournes them often. Then on the eyghteenth daye they doe hathe them in luke warme water, and on the one and twentith daye, they helpe to breake the ſhelles, and ſo takes them forth, and doth nouriſh them as other chic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens.</p>
               <p>Agayne they may do this another way whiche is, they marke the daye as they ſet them in the ouen, (as they doe another henne) and then they take ſo many egges as they thinke good to ſet, and ſettes them an ende in the ouen, on bagges of ſifted henne dongue, in compaſſing them round therewith, like a neaſte, and then they make a bedde of henne dongue, and layes it ouer the bagges, on the which bed they ſet their egges an ende, as before is decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and then they couer them with other henne dongue, and layes bagges thereon agayne, ſo that there doe no other thing
<pb facs="tcp:7695:16"/>touche them, then after the fourth and fift daye they turne the Egges gently once a daye, and ſets them ſo that one Egge doe not knock another, and at the fifteenth day the chickins will beginne to picke in the ſhels, then ye muſte helpe them forth, and breake the toppes of the ſhelles, and ſette them vnto another Henne that hath but a fewe chickens, and theſe chickens are in all thinges of theire owne proper na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ How to keepe egges long. <hi>Cap. 8.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe houſwife that woulde profite by keeping and ſelling of egges, ſhe muſt (as ſome ſaye) keepe them in a warme place in Winter, as in ſtrawe and ſuche lyke, well couered therein, and in the ſpring towarde ſommer, in freſhe branne, or meale according to the auncient coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, which vnder correction I beleeue the contrary, for the ſtraw is freſh and warme and the branue or meale is hote, it follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth then that egges kepte hote, will not endure nor laſt good ſo long as thoſe that
<pb facs="tcp:7695:17"/>are kepte colde, as thoſe whiche are kepte in drie ſalte, or to ſleke them in ſalie wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it doth deminiſh, but ye ſhall not doubt thoſe egges, to take any euill caſte there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, a ſweete ſelld is alſo good for to keepe them in both in winter and alſo in Som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.</p>
               <p>Againe, <hi>Columella</hi> ſayth, the manuer to keepe egges long tyme, is, in the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in ſtraw, and in ſommer in branne or meale, ſome doe put them fyrſt fiue or ſixe houres in fine beaten fault, and then they waſh them and lay them in ſtraw or bran, and ſome keepes them among beanes, and others keepe them in beane meale, and ſome doe lette them remayne in vnbeaten faulte, and other ſome doe ſoke them in brine or ſalte water, but like as cheſe doe keepe them from rotting, yet therby they will diminiſhe and waſte, and they wil not be ſo full of meate as thoſe whiche are newly layde: wherefore the beſt is, if they trouble you, to ſell them, becauſe thoſe which are put in brine, cannot ſo long be kepte full, but will waſte: hennes, duckes and others will laye without the Cocke, but will not be yong.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:7695:17"/>
               <head>Egges to gather and keepe. <hi>Cap. 9.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THeſe kinde of poultrie hennes are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed to lay egges all the yere but ſpecially in the ſpring they doe commonly begin (in could countreys) to laye firſte in Iaunarie, about the fifteenth daye, but if ye feede and nouriſhe them well, they wil lay ſouer, wherfore it ſhalbe good in brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging them forwarde to giue them barlye halfe ſodde, for that will make them hote, and to lay more ſooner and more oftner, and alſo greater Egges then others, but ye ſhall mixe with this Barlye, of Millet Wheate ſodde which will alſo heate, and encreaſe more courage in the hennes, and alſo to giue them of the other meate afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayde, which oughte to be giuen to the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers abrode, and to giue to eache henne 4. ounces of Barly, mixt with millet wheat: if ſo be you haue not fetches, giue them of the Wheate calde myl.</p>
               <p>Ye ſhall ſee alſo to ſo many as doe laye abrode, to haue from time to time of clean ſtraw in their neaſtes, and often chaunged
<pb facs="tcp:7695:18"/>with freſh ſtraw, for a laying henne doeth like that well, for it will keepe them from fleas and other like vermine, which often they bring with them when they come to their neaſtes to laye: ye ſhall marke alſo thoſe hens when they lay, although moſte hens doe giue a warning when they haue layde, in, cackling, and yet ſome Hennes wil hold their peace when they haue laid, and ſome hennes wil (whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they haue laid) but clock, wherefore ye muſt looke and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtte their Neaſtes when they haue layde, and then gather their egges together, and all thoſe hannes that haue layde that daye, for thoſe egges are beſt to bee putte vnder a henne that clocks, as for the other egges ye may ſell: the cheefeſt egges to hatche are thoſe whiche are neweſt layde, and yet ye may ſette other egs alſo which are older layd, ſo they be not aboue tenne dayes olde.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Egges to haue all Winter. <hi>Cap. 10.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HEnnes commonly begins to laye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Februarie and marche, &amp; then
<pb facs="tcp:7695:18"/>yong hennes lay a yere and halfe wel, and at the two yeres ende they are then better then at the firſt, and then muſt ye ſee that they be well fedde, as ſometime with good Ores mixte with Fenicreeke, to make them more hoter, and if ye will then haue them to laye greate egges, your Hennes muſt not be to fatte, for commonly pullets and fatte hennes will laye ſmall Egges, pullets becauſe they are but yong, and olde hennes becauſe they are ſo fat, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ye muſt mixe their meate with chalke &amp; put of beaten bricke into their troughes with ſome wine and water mixte, and ſo let them haue it daylye for a ſpace, or to giue them of Barlye halfe ſodde and mixt with tares, or the grayne calde millet. Wheate. Hennes doe commonlye ſeace laying about the third of Nouember, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the colde beginnes to come, and then fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding on blackbriers, elder, &amp; other fruite, but for being troubled, ye might chooſe of the faireſt hennes for to lay egges all the Winter, as well as at other times, which order is, ye muſt nouriſh them with toſted bread, and then ſoked ale or ſmall Wine, mixte with ſome water: Some doe take
<pb facs="tcp:7695:19"/>of Water and milke, and ſokes the toſtes therein, from the euening to the morning and ſo giues it them on the morrowe to their breakefaſt, and at night they giue them ſome otes, or barlye, and for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme ye muſt not let them be troden of the cock, and after the firſte laying alſo, lette them be kepte from the Cocke, and ſo they will long continue good, and when your hens are paſt three yeres it ſhall be beſt to ſell or to eate them, for after thoſe yeres they will hardly lay but waxe barren, therefore it ſhall be good to change them for youger hennes if ye can: &amp; againe, ſome do marke the places of thoſe hennes which are giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to lay mute, or make no noyſe, thoſe hens muſt not bee lette go abrode to ſeeke their neaſtes (for elſe ye ſhall haue ſmall profite of them) but only to bath them in the ſun, when the day is faire, and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to fee them had in againe. If a henne be troden of a crow, as ſome be, ſhe either dieth or waxeth barren, or proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:7695:19"/>
               <head>¶ Chickens of a later broode. <hi>Cap. 11.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THoſe Chickens that come of a later brood, ſome good huſwiues doth hold opynion, that they will be better layers, then thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> come in the ſpring, the other ſaith they are beſt for that purpoſe, if they may bee noriſhed and well fed in the firſt wynter, but yet by your leaue, they wilbe more tender in cold times, then the other that are bred in the ſpring: becauſe they are all winter brought vppe in the houſe, wherefore they are calde houſe chickens: but thoſe hennes that brings vppe their chickens abroad, and neuer comes in the houſe all ſommer, are the beſt, and they will bee muche fayrer and harder to lyue then the other brought vp in the houſe: &amp; alſo more profitable if ſhe can keepe them from ſpoyling till they be great.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>How to feed Chickens from the damme. <hi>Cap. 12.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TO feed &amp; nouriſhe Chickens from the damme, ye muſt vſe to giue them meat
<pb facs="tcp:7695:20"/>thriſe a day, in the morning, noone, and at night, and alſo to giue freſh water, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies ſette by their meate, ſo ſhall yee alwaies keepe them fayre and from the pippe: for when they haue eaten any meat they will deſire to drinke therevnto, and if they haue not alwayes freſhe water by them, they will ſeeke &amp; drinke of the next puddle and foule water they find, and that will ſoone breed in them the pippe, by the which it cauſeth a mortall poyſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in them, and it will make them droope, and hang their wings, &amp; at length dye thereof. And yee muſt clenſe out all the tares and dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell, from the barley and other meate ye giue them, and ſo feed them with the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaide meate till they waxe more ſtronger: ye muſt alſo perfume them with penneri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and roſemary, and to perfume your o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther poultrie, ye ſhall take Iſope, Linſeed or flaxe, and burne it, and hold the heads of your poultrie with their mouths open, ouer the ſaid fume, &amp; this will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue them alſo from the pippe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:7695:20"/>
               <head>¶ The pippe, and the cauſe, to helpe alſo. <hi>Cap. 13.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AL Poultrie are ſubiect to the pyppe on the tongue, which will grow on the end thereof like a thin ſcale, and it will let them to feed. One occaſion there is when they lacke drinke, or elſe when they haue dronke trobled or filthy water, or haue eaten of filthy and ſtinking meate out of the chanell, donghill, or other dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye place, whereas lyes the garbage of ſome filthy fleſhe, or ſuch like, or any e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll ſauoure will breed the pippe. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if ye fume your poultrie ſometimes with Sauine, Bayes, Roſemarye, or Gynnsper, it wyll ſaue them from the pippe.</p>
               <p>Alſo they ſaye the pippe will be a hard ſcale on the tip of their tongues &amp; to helpe the ſame, (ſome takes it of with his naile) and ſome do ſteepe a cloue of Garlicke in oile oliue, wherwith they chafe &amp; rub his bill, &amp; they do make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to eate of ſtaueſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aker among their meat, alſo <hi>Dioſcorides</hi> ſaith, the beries &amp; leaues of Priuet to bee
<pb facs="tcp:7695:21"/>giuen them, will preſerue both Cockes and capons from the pippe: againe, ſome doe vſe to giue them Garlike cut in pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces with butter, and giuen them when the pippe is take of, &amp; then with your mouth to ſpurt a little Ale, Wine, or Beare into their mouthes: Againe, other ſome doe raiſe the pippe ſoftely with their nayle, or the point of a Knife, &amp; ſo takes it off gent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and waſh it then with ale or beare, and ſo let him go, or to rubbe it with ſalte and Vinigere, or laye thereto of beaten Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lic whiche is counted good agaynſte the pippe: agayne others doe keepe the pippe whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is taken off, &amp; giues it him to drink with ale or beare, and they ſaye it will helpe, wherof they haue a prouerbe which ſayth, if he eate not the pippe, the pip will eate him: and alſo to ſaue them from the piype, ſome doe put into their throtes the blades of Garlick ſtieped in warme oyle, and doe ſprinckle their billes with mens brine warme, and then holdes them cloſe together along time after, ſo that by the bitterneſſe of the vrine, makes the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to caſte the pippe, and fleame at their noſe. Wilde grapes mixte with other meate, is good
<pb facs="tcp:7695:21"/>for them or beaten and ſtampte and ſo gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to drinke with water. Theſe are good remedies for poultrie that are ſieldome ſicke, if fleame haue already take their eyes, they will not then eate, then muſt ye ſlit their iawes to cauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matter to come forth that is gathered vnder their eyes, then rubbe it with a little beaton ſalt and parcelie, this greefe breedes commonlye when they abyde much colde, weate and hunger, or in ſommer when they drinke of a ſtanding puddle, or foule water, as is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſayde: agayne, Chickins when they waxe olde, are ſubiect to haue the Rie in their heade and eyes, catarres, rumes, and diſtillations, at their noſtrils: thorowe the colde and numneſſe of their feete, and to drinke the water of yſe, or froſen water, or too much colde taken thorow the faulte of the henhouſe, being to open in the night or ſitting abrode on Trees, or vnder the eaues of houſes when it raynes, and ſuche extreame colde, cauſes them to be more founded in their feete, which in ſome poul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie breedes the goute, ſpecially in tender byrdes, as yong Turquies and ſuche, and alſo the goute may come by the drinking
<pb facs="tcp:7695:22"/>of ice water, all theſe doe breede the like diſeaſes aforeſaide, whereby many dyes thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ To helpe the Catarre or rewme in poultrie. <hi>Cap. 14.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THey teache to put a penne croſſe tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row their noſtrils, and then they doe bathe them with luke warme water, and ſome tyme they do warme their feete, ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of ſuch as are yet yong and tender: and ſome doe vſe to lappe them in woollen clothes, wool, and in feathers, &amp; ſo keepes them in a veſſel by the fyre ſide, or in ſome warme ouen, or ſuch like place, then if the Catarre doe ſtill continue on the eyes and towardes the beake, ye muſt then gentlye cut it, and launce the impoſtume, and put that matter forth that is conieiled ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in and ſo put thereon a little beaten ſalt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:7695:22"/>
               <head>¶ How many hens to a Cock. <hi>Cap. 15.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>COlumella ſayth xii. hennes ſhall bee ſufficient for one good cock which will cauſe them the rather to be of one coloure, and yet ſayth he, our aunceſtors did vſe to giue but fiue hennes to one cocke, whiche cauſed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> rather to be of diuers coloures ſome white, ſome gray, ſome reddiſh, and ſome taunye, ſome blacke, and ſome of a ſpeckled colour, whiche are not thoughte to be ſo good as the red &amp; graye ſpeckled: and to haue hens all of one colour is beſt, and the hennes all of one colour (ſaue the white) are counted the beſt laiers. Again, <hi>Stephanus</hi> ſaith that twelue hens to one good Cock is ſufficient, and yet (ſayth he) our auncetours did giue but fiue Hens to a Cocke, whiche being ſo fewe (as ſome iudge) it did cauſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be neyther white nor gray, but part reddiſh tawnye, and blacke, which are (among the reſt) not counted the beſte Hennes to lay or breede.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:7695:23"/>
               <head>¶ Of Hennes that hatches abroad, as in buſhes. <hi>Cap. 16.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HEnnes that ſit abroad or other poul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trye, yee ſhall take hir and blindfilde hir ſoftly in the euening, &amp; take vp all hir egs, with ſo much of the neſt as ye can, &amp; then ſet her where ye ſhall ſeeme good, &amp; lay therein hir egs as they were before, and then ſet the henne ſoftly thereon, and decke the neſt with greene boughes like the place ſhe came from, and ſo ſhut hyr in all that night, on the next daye giue hyr meate and water: but let hir not forth the ſpace of three dayes, but giue her meate and water in the place, &amp; ſo ſhe will ſone forget the other place. Thus ye may haue hir &amp; hir chickens in more ſafty then to let hir ſit abroad: ye muſt not raſhly ſet all ſort of hens, but firſt learne &amp; knowe their natures, for ſome will ſit wel, &amp; ſone forget hir chickens: others wil bring vp &amp; nouriſh chickens better then ſit, &amp; ſome in ſitting will breake their egs as aforeſaide which are better to ſel the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſit: alſo aſſoone as a henne haue ended her fyrſte laye, ſhee
<pb facs="tcp:7695:23"/>will then couet to ſitte, wherein you muſt haue reaſon, and ſee that ye ſette her with no more egs then ſhe maye well couer, the number of egges that ye ought to ſette a henne, may not be aboue twentie &amp; three, and they ought to be all of one ſorte, as of one henne, and yet not always of one hens laying, for ye muſt giue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> according to the time in Ianuarie they giue vnto a hen xv. egges, in March xix. and in Aprill xxi. and ſo all the ſommer vnto the fyrſte daye of October xxi. and after that time no more, for if ye breede Chickins in the cold winter they are like to dye.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Cauſe of Fluxe in poultrie. <hi>Cap. 17.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ALſo the flux of the bellye in Poultry which thing doth make them weake it commeth oft times to poultry by eating of moyſte meate, or elſe they haue eaten of ſome laxatiue hearbes, or if their hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe haue bene left open all nighte, or ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſome colde ſitting vpon trees abrode, or in open places a nights, or elſe by ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of ſome fruite, theſe and ſuch like wil cauſe them to haue the fluxe, whiche doth
<pb facs="tcp:7695:24"/>much weaken them, whereby they will not lay ſo ſoone nor deſire the Cock.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Remedies againſt the fluxe. <hi>Cap. 18,</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Remedies are theſe, ye ſhall take and make powder of the huſkes of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cornes, then mixe it with barlye meale, &amp; with redde wine, ſo make a paſte thereof and giue it them, or caſt it vnto them cut in ſmale pieces, or giue vnto them the whites of egges hard roſted, &amp; then beate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with two partes of the curnels of great reyſons beate to fine powder, and ſo made in paſte as the other and caſt vnto them. Another, they make paſte of beaten barly, with chalk, &amp; mixt with the water where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Poungarnets or Quinces haue heene ſod in, and ſo do ye giue it vnto them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Againſt ſtopping of the belly in Poultrie. <hi>Cap. 19.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>YF your Poultrie be ſtopt in the vent &amp; cloſed vp, ſpecially oft times in young chickens. They do take and open the vent with a ſtrawe or ſuch like, and then clippe awaye all the fethers about the vent or
<pb facs="tcp:7695:24"/>tuell, and alſo on the inſides of both their thies, to the end their dung thereby bee not holden or kept long, which oft times is the cauſe of the ſtopping of the tuell, or vent, and for the ſtopping of the greater poultrie, they vſe to put a quantitie of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny among their water, &amp; alſo their meate, and that will helpe them againe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Againſt lice and vermine in Poultrie. <hi>Cap. 20.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WHereas lyce, fleas, hoggelice, ſowe wormes &amp; ſuche like, do trouble and hurt poultry, ſo that they cannot quietly feede nor reſt a nights, whereby they will wexe poore, whiche increaſeth when they cannot bathe in duſt, Sand, or aſhes, they get them alſo in ſcraping abroad among foule ſtrawe, or on dunghils, or gotten when they fit in neſts not made cleane, or in the henhouſe by their dung lying long there, which corruptes their vodyes, and breedes lice and fleas, the remedy, ye ſhall take y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pouder of pepper mixt with warme water, and therewith bathe them, or take fine pouder of ſtaueſaker, and mixe it with
<pb facs="tcp:7695:25"/>lye, and ſo waſhe them therewith, or to bathe them in ſope water, whiche is good to kill lyce, or the fine pouder of pryuer, mixte with viniger, and ſo waſhe them therewith, againe ſome doe waſhe them with Wyne wherein Commen is ſodde, and Staueſaker, or with the Water that wilde fetches or tares hath bene ſodde in, all theſe are good to kill lice and Fleas in poultrie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Of Vermine that bytes and ſtinges poultrie. <hi>Cap. 21.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>YE muſte alſo from tyme to tyme looke vnto your poultrie for ſtinging or by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with venemous worms, by haunting their houſes, and breeding in the dongue or olde walles, as ſpyders, Eftes, ſnakes, ſhroue mice which is venemous of nature and houſe mice or fielde mice, whiche will trouble poultrie, or Todes which will co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uet to ſit on warme egges: alſo agaynſte byting, ye ſhal annoint the venomed place with oyle of Scorpyon, or put thereon of Methridate, alſo giue them a little Tria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle with ale or beare, moreouer agaynſte
<pb facs="tcp:7695:25"/>Vermine that deuoures poultrie and egs in the henhouſe in the night, the auncy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents did counſell to ſtrew and ſet poſes of rew in the open holes or dore, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they councell to caſt of Bryne all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout on the walles and ſides of the henne-houſe, the dores and windows, and to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broy or annoynt the walles, and the dores and windowes of the henhouſe, with the gall of a Cat, dog, or Foxe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Of ſitting hennes that riſe in weat and raynie dayes. <hi>Cap. 22.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WHen as your hennes do ſit, after they haue ſate a day or two, yea three days or more ſomtimes, not riſing to eate, then hungar will conſtrayne them to riſe, and when they go abroade to ſeeke their meat and water, if the day be then weat, ye ſhal not ſuffer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to go abrode and weat their feete, for when as they returne vnto their neaſte, and touch their warme egges with their weat feete, the egges thereby maye ſoone chill, and thereby come to ſmall proofe, therefore in weat tymes and ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie
<pb facs="tcp:7695:26"/>dayes let not your hennes that fit goe abrode to ſeeke their meate, but ſet meate and water by them, ſo long as it is weate abrode: ſo ſhal their egges come to good, otherwiſe they ſhal be in daunger of chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling by hir weat feete, and therby come to naught, as thoſe egges whiche doe chill, whereas the henne in ſeeking meate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broade, is long abſent from her neaſte, in meane tyme they coole, and for thoſe hens that will breake their egs and eate them, ye ſhall make a neaſt egge, and playſter him all ouer with whytes of Egges bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with plaiſter and chalke, and layde thereon and dride in the ayre, and when it is harde it will be like the ſhell of an Eg, and make that the neaſt egge, ye maye make neaſte Egges of plaiſter and chalke, and vſe them as is before decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:7695:26"/>
               <head>¶ What time to carue yong Cock chic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins. <hi>Cap.</hi> 23.</head>
               <p>TO cut yong Cockrels to make them Capons, the time thereof is beſt to cut or carue them ſoone after their dam haue left them, or whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they cry or pule no more after her, as when they begin to crow and waxe hote to treade the pullets.</p>
               <p>The gelding or caruing of them is, to take away in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the hote deſire they haue to treade the pullets, and to make them chaſte, wherein there is two manner of wayes, which is not onelye to looſe their ſtones, but alſo when their ſpores is ſeard with a hote yron and ſo conſumed. Then after if any ſpur doe ſwell or rancle, yee ſhal couer it with potters earth or clay til it be hole. This way is more difficult, and yet vſed among the <hi>Greekes</hi> at <hi>Deloſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The common waye of cutting or car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing is not to be diſprayſed, and is moſte knowne as this waye: they take them in the morning commonly (the ſigne being good, and on the wane of the Moone) and layes the cock in hir lappe vpon his back,
<pb facs="tcp:7695:27"/>in truſſing vp his legges by his ſides, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the caruer pluckes firſte awaye the Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers aboue the vent, and takes vp the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſkinne with the poynt of the Needle, and ſlits it ouertwart an inche long, and then takes vp the vnder thin ſkinne, nexte the guts and ſlits that likewiſe, then the Earuer annoyntes her forefinger of her righte hande, with Oyle or butter, &amp; puts it gently to the raines of the cocke on the lefte ſide, and with her finger brings forth the ſtone. Then ſhe annoyntes the forefin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of her left hande, and puts it vnto the ſtone on the right ſide of the Cocke, and with her finger bringes it forth, ſo done, ſhe placeth the guts and ſowes the ſkinne vp agayne with a threede, and then an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noyntes that place with ſome freſhe but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and lets him go, but if the day then be colde or weate, keepe them in the houſe warme for a day or two after their Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, but if it be fayre, let them go abrode and when they are a yeare and a halfe old, there is no more diſpoſition or rankeneſſe in them, then ye may chooſe and take the moſte faireſt and greateſt Capon to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne and leade your Chickins, although
<pb facs="tcp:7695:27"/>there is not ſo great ſtoutneſſe in him, as in a cock.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Againſt the inflaming of the eyes and the hawe. <hi>Cap. 24.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AGaynſt the inflaming of the eyes in poultrie, ye ſhall boyle in water ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thernewood, and wheaten bread, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with bath their eyes, alſo ye maye bathe them with the diſtilled Water of pource<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layne and Womans milke, or with the iuice of Pourceleine mixte with a little hony, or the iuice of Sheapheardes purce mixte with Womans milke. And agaynſt the hawe in the eye, ye muſt rubbe the eye with bole Armoniac, Comyn and honey, beaten all well together, as much of the one as the other, and ſo lay it too, or if yee haue the practiſe to lift it vp warilye and lightly with the poynt of a needle, and ſo take it away, alſo the iuice of ground iuie with the Berries or leaues ſtampte with water or wine is better, and plaiſter wiſe lay it too, and remoue it once in <hi>24.</hi> hours and it will helpe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:7695:28"/>
               <head>¶ Cramming and fatting of Capons. <hi>Cap. 25.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WHen as ye take vppe your Capons to make them fatte, ye muſte prepare of wheaten meale, or barlye meale mixte with two partes of branne. Then ye ſhall heate ale or beare, but ale is the better, or luke warme Worte, and therewith tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per your meale and branne. Some do put therevnto freſh hogs greace, or of ſheepe, or oyle Oliue, and when it is all tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red together, they take a ſmall peece, and make and roll it betwixt their handes, of two inches long or more, and ſmal at both the endes, like this figure <gap reason="symbol" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap>, then they dippe it in milke, ale, or oyle, and giue a Capon ſo many thereof as ye ſhall thinke good, to a great Capon xx. roles, &amp; to the other as ye ſhall ſee cauſe: thus ye muſte feede them twiſe a daye at morning and euening, and ſo yee ſhall make them fatte in a moneth or leſſe, but alwayes ye muſte ſee that their meate is digeſted before yee giue them any more, for ſome be of a ſlow digeſtion, and if ye giue meate vpon meat
<pb facs="tcp:7695:28"/>they will loath it: Againe, they doe fatte Capons in ſome countreis, as in <hi>Mauce,</hi> and in <hi>Britaine</hi> (as they ſaye) when they woulde fatte them, they ſiele vppe their eyes, as they doe other byrdes, and ſo giues them meate to eate, as Corne halfe ſodde, and then made in paſte, and ſo into pellets like y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> other, or made in ſmall morſels, and feedes them therwith, and ſo they are made ſault in ſixe or ten dayes at the moſt, but ye muſt keepe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, and filing themſelues with their owne dongue.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Meate for hennes and other poultrie, and where and when to feede them. <hi>Cap. 26.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe beſt meate and feeding for, youre hennes is bruſed Barlye, or Fetches, or bruſed peaſe, likewiſe of wheate calde Millet, or the wheate panicke, theſe are the cheefeſt for them to eate, for theſe doe both heate and drie them, wherefore they vſe to ſiſte out the courſeſt of the wheate, and mixe it with the other, and to giue them all wheate it were to coſtlye, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb facs="tcp:7695:29"/>places, ye maye therefore giue them the ſeedes of cockle, with branne and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meale not much ſifted, but if there be not ſome meale with it mixte, it will not then giue them ſo good an appetite.</p>
               <p>And for thoſe hens that are leane, they doe giue them the leaues and ſeedes of Mellilot hearbe, for that is very good to make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue an appetite to their meate, and whereas ye cannot haue that, then ye may giue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the pomes of ſtraind grapes (if they laye not) or raiſons ſtampte with Barlye meale, for that will make them more giuen to lay, or if ye giue them the ſeedes of Raye, it will cauſe them alſo to laye, but after Autumne they lay then ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, becauſe they ſtraye abroade and eat berries and cold fruite not ripe, whiche makes them not diſpoſed to laye: then muſt ye giue them ſtore of meate twiſe a day in your court, morning and euening, to cauſe them to tarry that ſtrayes abrode then lette them not go farre from the hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe at night, not to tarrye long a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninges for their meate, for ſtraying a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brode, and haue no care of that place, and euery night for to tell them if ye haue all
<pb facs="tcp:7695:29"/>or not, for ſoone ye may be deceiued, alſo yee muſt ſayc Sande or Aſhes along the wall ſides for them to bathe in, for there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they clenſe their feathers from vermin and filth: if ye will beleetie <hi>Heracleus</hi> an <hi>Epheſian</hi> which ſayeth, that Hogges doe clenſe them in the myre and durte, &amp; poul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie doe clenſe them in ſande, aſhes, and duſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="chapter">
               <head>To fatte hennes beſt. <hi>Cap. 27.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BIcauſe it is the common office of the Councreyutan or woman to fat hens, and poultrie, ſo likewiſe it is for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> craftſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to buy keepe and ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> them, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it ſhall not be vinn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ete for both ſorts to feede them, ye ſhall hunderſtand ye muſt doe this: ye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> prepare a warme place and darke, and put each henne by her ſelfe in a penne; made ſo narrowe that ſhe can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not almoſt turnt her ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>, and thoſe pennes in u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> haue on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſides two holes the one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> forth her head, and the other her tag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>pe, and ſo to giue her meate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhe hath diſgreſted that in her
<pb facs="tcp:7695:30"/>craw, and to clenſe her penne ofte, that her dongue doe not hinder her fatting, ye muſt alſo put cleane ſtrawe vnder her, or ſofte haye of the later ſeaſon, for if they ſtande harde in the penne, they will ſcant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fatte, yee muſt place all the feathers on her heade and vnder her winges, and on hir thies, thoſe of her head and wings be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there ſhall come no Lice to trouble her, the other feathers on her thighes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the dongue ſhal not annoy and cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber her tuell, her meate ſhall bee Barlye meale made in paſt with water, and faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned in pellets long wayes, after this fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure <gap reason="symbol" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap> or as it is afore declares, for the feeding or cramming the Capon, and ſo to make hir to ſwallow them, the firſt daye it ſhall bee beſte to giue hir but little meate, vntil ſhe be accuſtomed to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt it, for aboue all yee muſt ſee that ſhee digeſt her meate well, and giue her no more ſo long as ſhe hath any meate in her croppe, and when ſhe is filde, let her go a little without the penne, ſo that ſhe go not farre, then if any thing pricke or bite her ſhe will complaine, and ſo yee maye helpe her, and thus ye may ſee the generall rule
<pb facs="tcp:7695:30"/>how to fatte hennes, and if ye will haue them fatte and tender withall, yee muſte kneade your barly meale with water and hony, and that will fatte them, and make them tender meate: ſome doe put into <hi>3.</hi> parts of water, one part of wyne, or ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g Ale, and ſtiepes wheaton breade therein, and that will alſo fat the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> well, if ye begin to fatte them in the new of the Moone, as it is counted beſt, ye ſhall haue her fatte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the twencith daye after, alſo in the meane time if ſhe doe refuſe her meate, ye muſt then diminiſhe or giue her leſſe, ſo many dayes as ye haue fedde her, the full time that ye ſhoulde fatte her, is but xxv. dayes, thus much for their meate, and fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of hens.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The feeding of bigge Chickins. <hi>Cap. 28.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe feeding or fatting of bigge Chic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens in the Coope or penne: They doe commonlye giue them ſteeped breade in Ale, ſometimes of drye breade, and their drinke milke and water, or of ſoked bran in milke, and ſomtimes ye muſt giue them
<pb facs="tcp:7695:31"/>barly, and to feele them one after another, if there be any thing in their crops, for if that which they haue eaten is not gone or conſumed, nor their craw yet emptie, that ſignifieth vndigeſted and like not y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> meat, then giue them no more till they haue di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted that, and for yonger Chickins that go yet with the damme, ye muſt not lette them go farre abrode, till they be ſtrong, but lette them remayne with the henne in the houſe, or pen, and giue them otemeale or Barly meale, till they be more ſtronger and keepe them as much as ye may from venemous wormes, as Adders, Suakes, Todes, and ſuche, for if they breathe and blow on them it is a poyſon come to them as euill as the peſtilence whiche killeth them, agaynſt ſuch venemous wormes the remedie is: ye ſhall burne in that place the horne of a Stagge in pouder, or of Gallamum or Womans heare, or hogges Dog, or Cats heare, for the ſmoke therof will cauſe the Snake or Adder to flie, and voyde, ye muſt ſee to haue them in tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate places, not to here nor to colde, for they may not (being yong) endure muche heate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> much colde, wherefore it were
<pb facs="tcp:7695:31"/>good to keepe them temperate in the pen with the dam fortye dayes, till they bee more able to go abrode, ye muſt alſo clip the downe betweene their theyes, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their rumpe, that their dongue waxe not harde, and ſtop the naturall Conduite, therefore yee muſt ſee ofte vnto them that their ventes may haue iſſue.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ To feede or cramme yong pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets. <hi>Cap. 29.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FOr the feeding and cramming of yong pullets a verye good way is this, to make them fat and tender to eate, ye ſhall keepe them in a darke place as aforeſayde or blindfield them: then take ground bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye ſmall, and ſifte our all the branne ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, then they doe vſe to moyſten the ſayde barlye meale with warme milke, &amp; ſome takes ale, and ſome beare, and ſo they cramm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and feede them as aforeſaid, mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and euening, in giuing to them ſo muche at once as they maye well digeſt and to helpe their digeſtion: ſome doe mixe with their meate of Muſtarde ſeede, or annie ſeedes: thus ye may fatte them in
<pb facs="tcp:7695:32"/>ſhort ſpace.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Ordring and letting forth Poultrie amorninges. <hi>Cap. 30.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>YOu that haue henhouſes, your hennes and poultrie ought to be lette forth a morninges with riſing of the ſunne, or within halfe an houre after, and to rooſte at night halfe an hower before ſunne ſet, this hath bene the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon vſe among far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers houſes in moſt countreyes, and in Autumne ſome will not let them forth of the henhouſe a dayes for a certaine time, but giues them meate and water there thriſe a day, or oftener then others, for they giue vnto each henne eight ounces of grayne a day, and thoſe that goes abroad but foure or ſixe ounces a daye, and thoſe that be kept in pennes to feede, to vſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as is before declared, and they oughte to haue on the Sunne ſide, a long windowe made with lath, that the ſunne maye ſhine on them, which will make them to picke and clenſe their feathers, and thereby wil like the better, and thoſe that ſhall looke
<pb facs="tcp:7695:32"/>vnto them muſt be painefull, clenlye and truſtie, otherwiſe there is ſmall profite or gaynes to be had by the breeding of them but trauell and datly charge, therefore ye muſt looke well vnto them alwayes, ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciallye, when they are yong and tender, for elſe there is no gains but loſſe, and time ſpent in vayne.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The order in caruing Poultrie of ſome here in Englande. <hi>Cap. 31.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SOme do vſe to carue or cut yong cock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels when they bee nye a quarter olde or more, as being hatched in marche, they carue them in Auguſt following, or when they doe growe in a heate, and wax proud and crowe often, or doe offer to treade the yong pullets, and rooſte before the hens, then it ſhall be beſt to carue them, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer them not to go to long (for as ſome do ſay) if they tread before they are cut, their fleſhe will not be ſo tender, and the older they waxe the more danger it ſhall bee to cutte them, wherefore to carue them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſhalbe alwayes beſt.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7695:33"/>
               <p>The order of caruing here in England of ſome is thus: they take them vp in the morning, then the caruer ſits downe on a low ſtoole, and another perſon holdes the body of the Cockrel in her lappe, bowing his feete cloſe by his ſides, &amp; holding them downe with his handes faſt on his bellye, and laying him on his back, and turning his tayle towardes the Caruer. Then the Caruer ſhall pluck away with her righte hand all the feathers and downe cleane from his pannell, the breadth of a ſhilling or more to make the ſkinne bare, then the Caruer takes a ſteele needle, and prickes thorow a part of the vpper ſkinne, and ſo takes it vp and cuttes it ouerthwarte his pannell, an inche and a halfe, and next his guts ye ſhal haue another thin ſkinne and take vp a part of that warily for pricking his guts, nor let him ſtriue as little as ye may, for if he do, he is in more daunger to proſper after, then the Caruer with the forefinger of the right hande ſhall ſpit or annoynt it with oyle, and with her finger lifte vp ſoftly his guts, in putting ſoftlye downe her forefinger vnto his raynes (on his lefte ſide) of his rompe, &amp; there plucks
<pb facs="tcp:7695:33"/>awaye his ſtone with her forefinger to the cut place, and ſo take it out with her fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finger and thombe, then the Caruer ſpits or annoyntes the forefinger of her lefte hand, and then puts it ſoftly downe to the raynes on the right ſide of the Cocke, and there takes vp the other Stone with her forefinger, as in the other ſide, if there be any, for ſome will haue but one ſtone, then put in his guttes and place them agayne, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with a needle and threed ſow vp cloſe the ſkinne againe, that no winde enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the waund, and beware in ſtitching his guts with the ſkinne, then annoynte it al ouer with freſh greace, and ſo let him or them go, but then if the time or daye bee colde, weat, or windie, the beſt is to keepe them in the houſe a day or two after, and giue them meate and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and they will bee nothing the worſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:7695:34"/>
               <head>¶ Other thinges neceſſarye to knowe for the keeping of Poultrie <hi>Cap. 32.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THoſe that will gayne and followe my counſell they muſt firſte conſider howe many hennes they may keepe, and then be ginne to nouriſhe them accordingly, fyrſte to know what time one oughte to gather egs to vſe and keepe: then after to hatche and howe they ſhoulde be ſette to the hen well, ſome in ſetting egges within xxiiii. houres, will take eche egge, and looke on them agaynſte a Candle or ſunne, if there appeare red ſtrekes in the egges, thoſe ſhe ſettes, and thoſe whith hath none, takes them awaye and eates them, &amp; when your heune hath hatcht, looke to the nouriſhing of your Chickens well, till they be able to do ſome pleaſure: in doing this, they ſhal gaine in gouerning well all your poultry about your houſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> number that hee muſt haue, he muſt conſider off: Manye Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers may well haue two hundred head of poultrie: to nouriſhe and gouerne this nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber well, it ſhall be ynough for one perſon
<pb facs="tcp:7695:34"/>to feede and ſaue them from daungers, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo take heede of being a white henne, for ſhe is counted no good layer, &amp; ſhe is ſeene farre of, whereby ſhee is in more daunger then others: and the blacke henne is no good layer, nor good to keepe, for ſhe is in daunger to be trodden of the fleſhe Crow, and then ſhee will neuer proſper after: therefore keepe ſuche hennes as are of a good colour breeders and layers, as the gray, the broune, and red feathered, &amp; ſuch and their bodies to be big and large, then they will lay the greater egges, their breaſt full and ſquare with a great head, her creaſtes redde and ſtraighte, and hir clawes to be indifferent greate, which is a good ſign in them, and thoſe which haue fiue clawes ſo they haue no ſpores grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the inſides of their legges for thoſe with ſpores, is a ſigne of males or male kynde, and they will ſieldome laye nor abide the treading of the cocke, and when they ſit they will breake their egges with their ſpurs, therefore chuſe to keepe thoſe that are beſt to nouriſh and laye, and ſell the reſt. Chickins after their hatching will lay within ſeuen moneths after, as
<pb facs="tcp:7695:35"/>being hatchte at Lammas, will laye at Marche nexte after, and in Autumne: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they ſeace laying by eating of fruit abroade, ſome doe thinke it good then to keepe a leſſe number, and ſell all aboue 3. yeres olde, and thoſe that ſieldome laye, &amp; not good to breede, or marre their egs in ſitting, and thoſe that crow like the cocke, or treade on other hennes, theſe ſortes of poultrie are not profitable, nor yet good to keepe, nor thoſe Chickens which are of a later broode, as hatched after the fifteenth day of September, for the time then will waxe colde, and they will ſmallye growe and encreaſe of bodye, but to keepe your Cocke chickins till they tread the hennes it ſhall be beſt, and then to chuſe the fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, the reaſon is: for ye ſhall hardly find a good cock, til ye haue ſeene their proofe, then to chuſe and take thoſe ye lyke amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g other, the red cocke is counted one of the beſt, and when your hennes doe ſeace lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by eating fruite in Autumue, ſome do keepe ſo many hennes in the houſe, as bee layers all the time of Autumne, and there giues them meate and water for a ſeaſon, and thereby they haue had plentie of egs,
<pb facs="tcp:7695:35"/>ſo that you kepe their houſe cleane, and for them that goeth abrode in Autumne, to geue them Corne it is but loſt, but let them ſhift for themſelues for that time, and thoſe ye kepe in the houſe, make their pearches and neaſtes, ſo that one ſitte not ouer another, for filing thoſe vnder, nor their pearches ſet nigh together, for by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting or fighting one with another of them whiche will cauſe them to haue leſſe loue to the houſe, and when yee haue boughte ſtraunge poultrie and yong, put them firſt in your henne houſe at nighte, ſtraude afore with ſome meate, which will make them after to loue the houſe, and ſo vſe them with meate two or three eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninges after, till they be acquainted with the henhouſe. Thus muche neceſſarye ſo knowe of the nature and gouernmente of poultrie. Alſo, if ye ſet Geeſe together in pennes, if one hatch before an other, thoſe that ſince will riſe from their egges and let them coole, and go with the other that hatched therefore let not one Gooſe ſee an other hatch before hen own be come forth: Barlye halfe ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and fedde, will make henne or ducke to laye greate Egges: if
<pb facs="tcp:7695:36"/>ye mixe it with the ſeede of Citiſus ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in frenche.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The nature and gouernmente of Geeſe. <hi>Cap. 33.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>GEeſe among other foule are moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable for huſbandmen and alſo for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, becauſe their bodyes is a common meate, they doe pleaſure to the Geutlema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and yeoman, and the greace profitable o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wayes, and among other water fowle thoſe which the <hi>Greekes</hi> doe call <hi>Amphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bia</hi> fowles of two kinde of liues, becauſe they feede as muche on the water, as on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lande. Among all other the Gooſe is moſt profitable for the buier, and alſo the ſeller and to the huſbandman, becauſe they neede not haue to great a charge and care for their meat as other muſt haue, for they do keepe as good a watche alwaye as the Crane or Dogge, all water Fowle muſte haue water, wherefore the Gooſe cannot liue or be kepte long withoute water and Graſſe, it ſhall not be good to keepe them where there is low brouſing hearbes, for they will croppe, kneble, and eate ſo farre
<pb facs="tcp:7695:36"/>and ſo hye as they may reache, but if yee haue any boyde grounde or place by ſome poude or lake where they may haue greſſe or corne to feede them, there it ſhalbe beſt for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be, I am of this opinyon, not by any great proofe, but becauſe I ſee they are kepte with ſmall payne and trauell, wherefore we may with ſmal charge haue both the Geeſe and their feathers, whiche feathers in ſome places they take not as ye take Corne in the fielde once a yeare, but fethers ſom takes twiſe a yere, which is, they elippe in Aprill, and pluck in Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt, for then they will come off lightlye, Geeſe where as they come they will ſtain the ground, and for that cauſe if the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey or place will not beare them, they ought to haue but certayne, as euery huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band man to haue one Gander, and three geeſe, becauſe they are a poiſon to grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds but to keepe in your ſeuerall Courte or houſes and yeardes ye may haue ſo many as ye ſhall ſeeme good.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:7695:37"/>
               <head>¶ Of places and houſes for or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of Geeſe. <hi>Cap. 34.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Columella</hi> ſayth, thoſe whiche hath a deſire to haue a number of Geeſe, or other water Foule, they oughte to make places and houſes for them to breede or fatte, and to bee vſed after this ſorte it would doe well, which is: ye muſt haue a large courte cloſe palde or walde of nyne foote hye, that no Vermine may enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, and all about within the ſame, to make allies and galleries with partitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and ſuch chambers for one alone to ſleepe in, and ouer the ſame to ſet your houſe for them made ſtrong with Stone or Bricke <hi>4.</hi> foote ſquare, plaſte about your courte, and to eche houſe a cloſe dore for them to come in and out to lay, and alſo to ſhutte them in when yee ſhall haue cauſe, then if there be not a ponde or riuer nye vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and to the houſe, yee muſt then make one elſe to ſeeke their water farre off, whiche is not good, for Geeſe that ſitte muſt haue water to bathe them, when they riſe from
<pb facs="tcp:7695:37"/>their neaſt, or elſe (as ſome ſay) their egs will not proſper, if there be no water, you muſt make a ponde, and clay it in the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome, for the water to remayne, and made ſomewhat deepe, that they maye plunge therein, for a ſaying is, a Gooſe will not like withoute bathing and waſhing her often, no more then a Beaſt withoute Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ A ground and paſture beſt. <hi>Cap. 35.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe grounde and paſture to nouriſhe Geeſe beſt, is that which is like a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhe or moyſte grounde repleniſhed with graſſe and other hearbes, alſo ye muſt ſow other kinde of feeding for them, as Fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, mellilot, the three leaued graſſe and fenigreke, and ſpecially of Citory, which the <hi>Greekes</hi> call Cerys, alſo it ſhall bee good to ſow of Lettiſe, for that is a tender hearbe for the Goſlings, and Geeſe doeth loue them well, al other poulſe is meate for them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:7695:38"/>
               <head>¶ To chooſe Ganders and Geeſe with all white Feathers. <hi>Cap. 36.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>STephanus</hi> ſayeth, yee muſt prouide to haue of the greateſt Ganders &amp; Geeſe that ye can get, and thoſe which are white feathered, yet ye ſhal haue many do breede blacke Geeſe, and haue them as tame as the other, but they come of the wild kinde and are ſkant ſo fruiteful as the other, nor ſo good to haue, wherfore nouriſhe as few of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> black Geeſe as ye may, becauſe their fleſhe is not ſo good, for it is more dryer, nor their feathers ſo holeſome for beds as the other. The gooſe is very profitable for the huſbandman and others, and alſo they are great marrers of groundes, of profite, becauſe there is no greate charge or care in breeding them, and they yielde mauye Egges, and bring forth manye yong, to greate profite, for their Feathers ſerues many wayes, for beds, for Arrowes, and quils for writers: and they are alſo hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vnto groundes, in ſtayning and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Medowes, and Fieldes with theire
<pb facs="tcp:7695:38"/>dongue, if they be not kepte oute, they bruſe hearbes in gardens and ſpoile corne in Fields, their dongue ſtayne al grounds where they come, ſo that no Beaſt will ſcant feede after them, the wylde hurte common fieldes, a number of them in half a day will deſtroy a great peece of wheat, if it be but lowe, and the houſe Geeſe is more hurtfull, for they in feeding will pluck vp the rootes of Corne, with the blades, &amp; where they dongue there comes nothing after, but euill weedes: the Gan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders are louing to all the yong Goſlings: they are better to be all white then gray, or mixte with two coloures, and the black coloure is worſte of all, and of leaſte good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The laying and ſetting of Geeſe, and feeding the yong Goſlings. <hi>Cap. 37,</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Gooſe doth laye at three times in the ſpring, if ſhe doe not ſitte, at fyrſte ſhe will lay fiue Egges, then foure, and then but three, and ſome will lay at eache time twelue egges, and ſome more, which
<pb facs="tcp:7695:39"/>time is from the fyrſte of March, vnto the ende of Iune, and then no more, wherfore ye ſhall not forget her fyrſte laye, but ſet them, for they will prooue beſt, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time beſt to ſet your Geeſe, is after winter is gone, as from the firſte of Marche vnto Iune, and not after, and when they haue layde their later laye, they will couet to ſitte, all the reſt of the yeare they lay not, yee muſte alſo looke well to their laying, that they laye not abrode, for when they are enclinde to laye, they will take vppe ſtrawes as they goe, and will caſt them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide here and there, on eache ſide of them, and ſoone after then they will laye, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore towarde night ye muſt take them vp, and feele how many be ready to lay, which ye ſhall perceiue if ſhee be nye laying, yee ſhall feele the ende of hev egge harde at her vent, then ſhut her vp, and putte her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone in a neaſt till ſhe haue layd, ſo ſhe wil ſeeke that place agayne to lay, where ſhee haue bene before, and when you ſette her take heede of her egges, for ye muſt ſette her of her owne egges, for a Gooſe loues not to ſitte but of her owne egges, if yee ſet her of others, ye muſt haue part of hirs
<pb facs="tcp:7695:39"/>withall, and then marke al the other egs, or elſe hers with ynke or ſuche like, for they ſaye, a Gooſe will not hatche the egs of another, if ſhe ſitte not of her own with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all. They ſet the Gooſe on her egges, as the pehenne on her egs, with fiue or more vnder her, but at leaſt they ſette her with three egges, ye maye ſet a Gooſe with ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen or nyne egges, and the moſte doe ſet a Gooſe but with fifteene Egges, ye muſte alſo remember when yee ſette her, to laye in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtraw vnder hir of ſtrong nette rootes, which will (in hatching) preſerue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linges &amp; is ſpeciall good againſte the ſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging with nettles, for thereby (they ſaye) they ſhall take leſſe hurt by ſtinging, and if there chaunce any to be ſtong, they dye thereof commonly ſoone after.</p>
               <p>To hatch in colde times the Gooſe wil haue then thirtie dayes, and in temperate tymes ſhe will hatche (being well vſed) in xxv. dayes at the moſte, and when they are hatched they muſt not then go abrode, or forth of the penne, houſe, or courte, the ſpace of tenne dayes till they waxe more ſtronger, but feede them in the houſe with the Dam, and giue them Barly meale, or
<pb facs="tcp:7695:40"/>ote meale, or ſtieped wheate, ſome do giue them Garden creſſe chopte ſmall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, whiche will make them to haue an appetite, they giue them ſometime of ſtie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped barlye, or mault, or meale, chopt with Hemtockes and ſo giuen, or elſe with bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye meale ſtieped, and mixed with honyed water, it ſhal be good to keepe them in the houſe with the damme, and there to feede them with meate and water, till they may flie the daunger of Crowes and Kites, for when they are ſmall, the fleſhe crowe will fette them away, if any remayne behynde the damme: and when they are able to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyde the crowe, then ye may let them go abrode with the damme, or in a fayre daye being yong, yee maye put them abroade with the dam, hauing one to keepe them, and ſetting a Baſon of water and meat by them, or elſe not put abrode, and yee muſt looke they be not ſtung with nettles, or ſcrat with briers and thornes, nor when they haue great hunger to let them go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brode, but to giue them Succorye ſmall chope, or the tender leaues of Lettiſe, if ye then let them go abrode to feede in pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures being yong and hungrie, they will
<pb facs="tcp:7695:40"/>force themſelues to plucke at hearbes, which grow faſt, and ſo falles backe, and lye ſprauling on their backes, are ſo taken with Kytes and Crowes. Therefore it ſhall be more ſure to keepe them with the Damme in the houſe till they are more of ſtrength, and giue them of mill wheat, or other wheate ſteept in water and ſette by them, &amp; when they are more ſtronger, yee may put them in houſes with others to fat as heereafter ſhall appeare. <hi>Stephanus</hi> ſaith, at the months end ye may then choſe your yong geeſe &amp; fatte them, then take the faireſt and put them vp into a court or penne, and fatte them, for the yonger ſort of geeſe ye may fatte them in xxx. dayes, &amp; the elder ſorte in two moneths, yee muſt giue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> meate thriſe aday, of barly mele and whay, or to giue them ſteeped wheate in water and honey. The barly doth make their fleſhe white, and the whaye doth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhe and fatte them. Some do take figges new dride, and thereof makes a paſte and giues them, and their drinke muſt be bran and water: and ſome when they doe fatte them, do pluck their fethers of their heds and bellies, and the great fethers of their
<pb facs="tcp:7695:41"/>winges, and then ſieles vp the eyes of the old Geeſe when they fat them, and giues them beanes and peaſe and fayre water, which is a good fatting meate for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey Gooſe, and alſo they feede them with all ſorts of poulſe, firſt ſoked in warm wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and branne which doe feede them wel, and manye doe giue them branne alone, made ſomewhat fatte, and doth alſo giue them of lettiſe, of Succorye, or Creſſis to make them haue an appetite, and feedes them ſo thriſe a day.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The fatting of yong Geeſe. <hi>Cap. 38.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>COlumella</hi> ſayeth, when yong Geeſe are foure moneths olde, then they take the greateſt and fayreſt to fatte them, for while they are yet but yong, it is the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter fatting of them, then when they are more older, and theſe neede not to haue no other thing but Barlye meale, and the flower of meale, and to be fedde therewith thriſe a daye, and they muſt haue drinke continually with their meate, ye muſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo keepe them in a cloſe houſe or dark pen,
<pb facs="tcp:7695:41"/>and kepte warme withall, which ſerueth much to make them forwarde to fatte, and thus in two moneths ye may fat the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> well, or in ſixe weekes, the ſooner when they are yong and tender, then when they are tough and olde, and ſome will chaunge their meate often, and they will feede the better, and be the ſooner fatte.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ How manye Geeſe to one Gander, with other gouernment. <hi>Cap. 39.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>OUr Aunceters did giue but 3. Geeſe to one gander, and we giue ſixe, but for marring &amp; ſtaining of medowes, paſtures, and fields, they are profitable for the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band and keeper of houſe, as anye other fowle, and they require a ſmall tending, but when they are yong, for the ſpace of 3 weekes, or a moneth, and ſo long to haue a keeper till they be oute of daunger of the Crow and Rite, and to keepe them from eating euill weedes, as henbane which is calde the death of Geeſe, and Hemlocke which is not good for them to eate muche thereof, for it will make them ſleepe ſo
<pb facs="tcp:7695:42"/>much, that they may be ſoone taken, and are in daunger (as ſome ſay) to dye there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, to haue manye in a flocke is not good, they vſe not aboue thirtie Geeſe in one flocke, and our Aunceters did vſe but xx. in a flocke, for the bigger will beate, and be mayſter alwayes of the leſſer, both a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brode and in houſes, therefore it ſhall bee good to part eche breeding houſes by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, whiche houſes muſte be alwayes kept dry, for they loue to ſit drie a nights, and to be ſtrewd with freſh and ſoft ſtraw, or with ſofte hay, and oft to be clenſed for breeding of Vermine, becauſe that Geeſe are more ſubiect therevnto, then the hens are, the reſt of their gouernement &amp; meate is like vnto other fowle, and take heede of bryers, nettles, Snakes, and other vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous wormes, while they are yong, for a ſmall thing killes them ſoone after their hatching.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:7695:42"/>
               <head>¶ Of the feathers of Geeſe, whiche are beſt, and what time to pluck them. <hi>Cap. 40.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe profite that manye good huſwittes doe finde by Geeſe feathers and others is this: they vſe in many places yearely to take a fleece of their Geeſe, as men doe of their ſheepe, whiche feathers commonlye they take in Iuly and Auguſt, and in ſome places they take their Geeſe feathers twiſe a yeare, in marche they clip all ſaue their bellies, to couer their yong, &amp; they plucke in Auguſt, and ſome doe plucke in Marche, and ſayeth their feathers will come the ſooner or rather then when they are clipte, for in clipping the quilles re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne ſtill till melting time, wherefore plucking them is rather counted better (then clipping) to haue two fleeſes a yere. Thus yee maye vſe them as ye ſhall ſee cauſe, to haue their fethers for a more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite to furniſh yearely your beddes which are occupied dayly, as in Innes and ſuch,
<pb facs="tcp:7695:43"/>but whereas there are greate pondes or riuers nye your houſe, it is great danger to pluck the feathers of their bellies, for whereas ſuch cold waters are, it is a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to kill them, as experience hath ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in ſome places of this realme, therfore if ye plucke their bellies, to keepe them from ſuch places for a time it ſhal do beſt. Of all feathers the ſwanne is the cheefeſt, and the feathers of the white Gooſe next, the black or gray Gooſe feather next him and the Capon and pullet next, likewiſe al other lande fowle, then Ducke, Wegin, Teale, and ſuch water fowle are next, and are beſt to be rather put in cuſhions then in beds, becauſe they are more hotter, and a greater ſoker of men in beds, then the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the Pigion worſte feather of all, for they ſoke too muche to be put in beds, and are vnwholeſome, for they ſay if a ſick perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lye on a pillow of pigions feathers, he ſhall long continue ſo without depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, which thing I hardly beleeue, and likewiſe all ſick feathers or bloodye Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are not good to be put in beds, nor Coſhions, becauſe they doe commonlye breede wormes, therefore it is not good
<pb facs="tcp:7695:43"/>to put any in beds or coſhions: thus much concearning the nature and goodneſſe of the Goſe feather and others.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Of Duckes, Teales, Sheldrakes, and ſuch like, <hi>Cap. 41.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">Columella.</head>
               <p>TAme Duckes (among the reſt of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter fowle) is moſte profitable for the huſband mans houſe, and for once a yeere they are layers of many egges, and bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders alſo of many young, with a ſmall at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendaunce as the gooſe, ſaue in the time while they are young, and to haue the like places conuenient to nouriſhe them in as the gooſe, but ſomwhat more chargeable, becauſe they are great feeders, and for all other ſorts of water foule, as wilde ducks ſheldrakes, wigions, morehennes, cootes, and ſuch fowle of the ponds: ye ſhal hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye make them tame being olde, and lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe all other byrdes that vſeth to feede in waters and marreſhes, which are calde of our auncientes, byrdes of double liuing or nouriſhment, to nouriſh and keepe ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:7695:44"/>which are accuſtomed ſo to feed, and keepe them in houſe, ye muſt chuſe a playn place cloſed about with hye walles of xv. foote and couered aboue with railes, wyar, or nets of big corde, to the end they flye not out, nor eagles, Rites, bozards, or crowes, ſhall come in, and all the walles without and within ought to be poliſhed ſmooth, to the end that cattes, or other venemous wormes may not catch hold and climbe to come in, and in the midſt of the ſame court yee muſt make a ponde of two foote deepe, So long &amp; wyde as the place will ſerue, and that the water there may run ful con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually to the brinime thereof, that the bankes may not be marde, and alſo made with plaiſter, and cimmond in the bottom, and all about the ſides, paued with ſmooth ſtone, that no weeds do grow therein, but that the fowle may haue cleere water ſtill run thorow, and in the midſt ye ſhal make a mount of earth, &amp; thereon ſowe beanes of Egip, and ſuch other greene herbes as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly comes in waters, to couer &amp; hide thoſe fowle therin: for ſome of them loues to be hid in tuftes of graſſe, roſes, ſedge, and ſuch: notwithanding ye muſte not co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb facs="tcp:7695:44"/>their holes, for (as I haue ſaide) the water muſt be all the day without weeds, to this end, that in the heate of the daye, when they would come forth to bathe and picke them they maye then ſwimme and plunge in the cleere water at pleaſure, for ſo it is beſt agreing to their nature, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as they may enter into water at their wil to take pleaſure and watch for ſmall fiſhe therein, or flies vppon the water. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ye ſhall do them great wrong, to put them where they cannot come to the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter when they woulde, and all about be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath at the bottom of the walles, ye ſhall make holes xx. foote from the water, and all the ſides couered with berbes, and by the wall ſides to make holes of ſtone, a foote ſquare, then couer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to make their neſtes therein, and garniſhed all aboute with boughes and braunches which they will like the better, and yee muſt make a channell for to conuay the running water. &amp; vſe to feed your fowle in the ſaide water as other fowle, &amp; to giue them myll wheat or pannicke wheat, or other grayne, and feed them in the ſaide water, or with bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ground cornes, and pomes of reaſons,
<pb facs="tcp:7695:45"/>which is alſo good for fiſhe, which ye ſhall put in the water (to feede them) of Creuis ſhrimpes, loches, Menues, banſticles, and ſuch riuer or brooke fiſhe, whiche will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer waxe bigge, all theſe they will take pleaſure to hunt after in the water. The wylde Ducke when ſhe layes, the Drake ſhall not know, for if he might knowe, hee woulde ſucke all her egges, they treade in the time of the ſpring, as other wylde Fowle doe, in Marche or after, in whiche time ye muſt caſt vnto them of ruſhes, or ventes, and ſmall twigs into their court, which they will gather, and make their neaſtes withall. There is an ancient rule that whenſoeuer ye woulde haue a greate flocke of theſe fowle, yee muſte gather of wylde Ducke egges where they lay, and put them to a henne to hatche, and when they are hatched, they will then leaue their wildneſſe with vſe of the henne, and then when they waxe bigge, ye maye put them into your cloſe Courte, as I haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſayde, and theſe will breede and mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplie, for if ye take wilde Duckes which are accuſtomed to liue at libertie, and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhut vp in a cloſe place, they will neuer
<pb facs="tcp:7695:45"/>laye, being ſo kept, very few or none. A ſaying is, if ye touche the egges of a wild Ducke when ſhee layes, with your bare hande, ſhe will not come and laye no more there, and if ye take awaye ſtill her egges and leaue but one, ſhe will ſtill lay till ſhee be ſo poore, that yee ſhall take her on the neaſt. This ſhall ſuffice here for the kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of the Duckes, and other Water Fowle.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ How to take your wilde Ducks in the Court. <hi>Cap. 42.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">Stephanus.</head>
               <p>WHen as you would haue any of youre wilde Duckes taken, to make them more tamer, ye ſhall caſt (in the court) vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them graine mixt with the lies of wine ſweete wyne, or ſower, and lay it on their accuſtomed place to feede, giue them alſo paſte made with Wine, or a leuin paſte with branue and Wine lyes, caſt it in the ſayde place, and when they haue eaten thereof, they will be dronke, then ye maye take and chuſe of the beſt withoute greate
<pb facs="tcp:7695:46"/>trouble of the other fowle.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The common feeding and the nature of Duckes. <hi>Cap. 43.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Ducke is a groſſe, greedye, and filthie feeder, and a hote Byrde of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and ſtill will be eating. They vſe to feede them with all kinde of pulce, as yee feede a hogge, and to haue them fatte they geue them gurgions of corne, but ye muſt alwayes let them haue water by them, for they muſt ſtill bee drinking as they eate, they loue alſo to wander in ſommer in the euening, in Auguſt and September to ſeeke after Wormes, Beetles, Frogs and Todes, and they wil eate them, and when ſhe hath hatched, ſhee is carefull of her yong, if any of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yong be ſtong or angerde they be ſo peuiſhe, they will dye ſtraighte waye, and yet many lets them go with the dam into Waters or pooles, being but two or three dayes olde: ſhe will make her neaſt her ſelfe, againſte ſhe laye and ſitte, and ſo ſhe hatches in xxv. dayes, or xxviii. at the moſt.</p>
               <p>The wilde Ducke will ſteale from the
<pb facs="tcp:7695:46"/>Drake, and when ſhe hath layd and hatcht ſhe is very ſubtle when ſhe hath yong, for if any perſon come nye them, ſhee will flie flappering nye before him on the grounde as though her backe were broken &amp; could not flie, thus will ſhe tiſe him a good way from her yong, and then will ſhe take her flighte to her young agayne. Duckes egges hatchte vnder a henne will bee of a better meate, then thoſe hatched with a Ducke. Duckes are not good to bring vp chickens, for ſhe cannot call as the henne will to euery crumme ſhe findes, and the Ducke loues the water, and the Chickin the Land, nor the Duck cannot ſcrape as the henne will, nor the hen good to bring vp Ducklinges, for ſhe loues not to go in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the water with them, and thereby ofte times they are taken away with the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard, or Ryte, when ſhe cannot help them, and thoſe Ducks that haue bene brought vp vnder a henne, the Drakes of that broode will deſire to tread the hennes, and one Drake is ſufficient for vi. Ducks, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo Duckes that are trod of the Crow, they neuer proſper, and are vuwholeſome to eate, as they ſay, agayne they ſaye, the
<pb facs="tcp:7695:47"/>Ducklinges that are brought vp vnder a henne, they will bee alwayes deſirous to bee about the houſe, and on the dry ground nye the houſe not abroade, nor yet in wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, which is their nature, whereby your houſe and courtes cannot bee long cleane kept where they vſe, and yet by nature they ſhould co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly loue the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Thus much for the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and feeeing of Duckes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:7695:47"/>
               <head>¶ <hi>Of Turquie hennes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite</hi> and alſo diſprofite. <hi>Cap. 44.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>STephanus ſaith, they that firſt brought theſe Turquies into Fraunce, calde the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the peacocks of Indie, whiche doth rather enrich the mouth, then any great profit to the farmer or breeder: for they are a right cofer for oates, &amp; a ſack for corne, a gulfe, a ſwallower of barns, a deuourer of much meat. They cannot receiue ſo much plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure by them, but as much trouble and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they are great, for they be great ſtrayers abroad, &amp; being young they are alwaies crying for meate, with puling &amp; complayning of the rye, or goute, or ſuche like, and ſoone dye thereof if they bee not well kept. True it is, their fleſhe is deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, but heauy and harde of digeſtion: therfore they muſt be well baſted and lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and yet there is muche more goodnes in the fleſhe of Peacockes, then in them. They were brought into England about the eight and twenty yeere of the raigne
<pb facs="tcp:7695:48"/>of king Henry the eight.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="45" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The nouriſhing of olde Turquies. <hi>Cap. 45.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe nouriſhing of theſe fowle, is like the feeding of hennes and other poul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, and with the lyke meate when they are bigge, and as much tendaunce or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly more, becauſe they will ſtraye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad to ſeeke their meate, it may be well ſayde to the farmer or breeder: ſo manye Turquyes in his court, ſo manye moile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coltes in hys ſtable to feede. Their tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in deede is more eaſyer then of other Peacockes, nor doth not demaund ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen ayre, but their feeding is a more grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter deſtruction in Gardens, of leekes, oni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, &amp; al other kinds of other good herbs, which they will eate, and wyll commonly feede of graſſe, as well as the gooſe, &amp; are as fulſome in the houſe as the geeſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="46" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The age of Turquie cockes beſt to treade. <hi>Cap. 46.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>YOur Turquie cockes that ye keepe to
<pb facs="tcp:7695:48"/>treade your heunes, ought not to be paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing a yere, or two yeres old, three yeeres is the moſte or too muche, for being olde they are ſo heauy in treading, they wyll commonlye hurt the hennes, in brooſing their backes and treading of theyr fethers of their backes, and alſo it is not good to keepe two cockes in treading time: for one will hinder the other, ſo ſhal your hennes egges come to ſmal profite in ſetting, and yee ſhall haue ſome cockes will pecke and kill the chickens if they be put forth being very yong, and againe ye ſhall haue ſome cockes will loue and keepe their chickens as tender as the hennes. Therefore bee ſure to know your cocke to loue the chic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins, when ye put them forth yong, and alſo when they goe feeding abrode, they will not lightlye keepe one place to rooſte in, as other poultrie will, wherefore yee muſt daylye looke vnto them for leaſing, for ſometime they will ſit in high wayes on the ground, ſometime on lowe places nye the ground, and here is to be noted, ye muſt not vſe your hogges to feede on car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren or dead fleſh about your houſe, for if they catche eating of fleſhe, they will not
<pb facs="tcp:7695:49"/>ſticke to eate your poultrie on their neſts, or your Turquies when they ſitte on the ground a nights, or any lowe places nigh the earth, and they will not ſtyrre if yee touche them, wherefore they are in more daunger of ſtealing or deuouring diuers wayes, then other poultrie are.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="47" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Of the Turquie hennes ſitting, hat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, and nouriſhing the chic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens. <hi>Cap. 47.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Turquie hennes doe commonlye laye as the houſe hennes doe, but they will commonly lay away in ſecrete places of their own ſeeking, as in buſhes, hedges and ſuch, if ye looke not well vnto them. They begin to lay in Marche, and they doe vſe to ſet them in Aprill when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great colde is paſt on nine or eleuen egges, ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times more, they doe hatche in xxv. dayes, and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they haue hatched, ye muſt feede them with curdes ſoked in ſtrong ale or wyne, and ſuch tender meate, as ſod wheat in ale or beare, for the hennes will neuer call or feede their yong (as other hennes will) therefore yee muſt giue them often
<pb facs="tcp:7695:49"/>meate being yong in ſixe or eyghte dayes till they waxe more of ſtrength, and then ye maye giue them ſod barlye, and more ſtronger meate, the dew will kill them, if they eate thereof, and to bring vppe youre Turquie chickens in the houſe, they will not like ſo well, as to lette them goe with the Damme in ſome ſafe place abrode, and better they will like abrode then in the houſe, but in wete and cold times ye muſt ſee them kept warm a nights, or elſe they will ſoone catche the goute, crampe, or the rye, and being yet yong they can bide no colde abrode, alſo thoſe hennes that lai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth their later laye and ſitte, they bring vp their chickens about mid Auguſte, or after, which chickins are ſo tender in win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter following they will hardly proſper, for they may abide no colde, but haue the like diſeaſes aforeſayde, therefore to ſell or eate them is beſt, the beſt time for Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quie hennes to hatche (here in Englande) is in Aprill, when the cheefe colde is paſt, and alſo to houſe them in winter is beſt, to keepe them from the diſeaſes afore men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned.</p>
               <p>When as any of your Turquies haue
<pb facs="tcp:7695:50"/>the rie and therewith droope, yee ſhall make a long pellet or two, with ſope, but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and pepper, mixe them altogether, and ſo giue it them a morninges, and they wil mende, and if your Turquies be greate, and hauing ſwoln eyes in winter by cold, ye ſhall ſlit it with a ſharpe Knife, then ſhall yee ſee the humoure leape out, then waſhe it with ale, or wine, and if it fill a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, open ſtill &amp; waſh it till it be whole, alſo when they begin to droope, yee ſhall put downe theire throtes, two or three of ſow wormes with manye feete, and then take fennyll a little, &amp; brooſe it, then make it like a pellot, and put it after down their throtes, and ſo let them go and they wyll amend. Thus ye may keepe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſafe (with good looking to) from tyme to tyme, tyll they be great as the damme.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="48" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The feeding and the ordering of Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quie hennes and chickens. <hi>Cap. 48.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THey vſe in ſome places to giue the Turquie chickens new hatched curds and antes egges, for ſeuen or eight daies, of barly meale, mixte with penniriall, and
<pb facs="tcp:7695:50"/>made in paſte with good ale or wine, litle prinke but curdes, and antes egges, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o giue them mellilot herbe with otemele <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd milke, which is a greate feeder: or I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſope, or to giue them of percely, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times they giue them chopt onions, leeke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lades, time, and ſuche like: any of thoſe chopt ſmall with the, foreſaide barly mele or otemele, and tempered with ſtrong ale, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r beere, and made in paſte (as aforeſaide) and ſo giuen in ſmale pellots, it will ſaue them and deliuer them from the rye, pippe and ſwelling in their heades, &amp; the goute in their feete, which commonlye comes of cold and to much drinke: alſo in winter ye maye mixe with their meate a little aqua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ite with ale, which will in likewiſe ſaue them from the the rhume, &amp; other diſeaſes: moreouer when as any haue taken colde on their feete being but young, if yee rub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>his legges and feete (with neats oyle) in wet and colde times, it will ſaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from the crampe, and when they are greate and olde, Some (for want of other meate) doe feede them in winter with hawes, and heps, black beries, nut Kernels, acornes, &amp; ſuch, which thinges they will eate, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:7695:51"/>himgry, for they are hotte birdes of nature &amp; great raueners withall, among the hennes, the white Turquie henne is exteemed better then the other coloures, to hatch and bring vp their chickens: for they are of a more harder and kinder na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture then the other commonly are, &amp; wyll kepe their chickens better: alſo if a Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quie henne do hatch and bring vppe other henne chickens with hers, when they wax bigge, ſhe will knowe they are none of hir kinde, and ſhe will beate them and driue them away, and ſo long as your turquye chickens be young, yee ſhall geue them of ſod barly in ale or beere, or ſtieped in wine and it will preſerue them from thoſe dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, which commonly they are troubled with all heere in England, for our coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey is more colder (as it ſhoulde ſeeme) then from whence they came firſt, and ſo long as they are yet young, they are ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and ſoone hurt by venom &amp; ſting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wyth nettels and ſuche, till they be a quarter old or more.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="49" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:7695:51"/>
               <head>¶ The common feeding of Turquies. <hi>Cap, 49.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe nouriſhing and common feeding of thoſe kinde of fowle, is as I haue ſayd like the feeding of other poultrie &amp; hens, and with as much or more diligence, elſe there is no difference, but they muſte haue much more meate, and their training is eaſie: but to haue tendance while they are yet young, their maner of feeding I haue afore declared: they are filthy birdes in a houſe, wherefore the maide muſt come al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies after them with a beeſome, to clenſe where they haue been, the hennes will lay like our hennes, if they bee well kept all the yeere: and when they haue layde a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine time, they will couet to ſit, and yee may vſe them as you do other hennes, and to giue their egges vnto other hennes to ſit &amp; gouerne while ſhe end hir lay. Their diſeaſes and remedies are like other poul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wherfore it is ſuperfluous to ſay here any more, but as ſome do ſay, when they are very fat, they will not lay ſo well nor take the cocke, as when they are kept in a meane.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="50" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:7695:52"/>
               <head>¶ Of Peacockes the nature and feeding <hi>Cap.</hi> 50.</head>
               <p>THe Peacocke is a ſtrange bird to ſeed and to gouerne, for they hardly bee ſo familier with any perſon, as other birdes will. A breefe reherſall of <hi>Columella,</hi> which ſaieth, to nouriſhe peacockes requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth a more dilligence in a Ciuile perſon, then in a rude &amp; troubleſome farmer: for it is the part of a good keeper of birdes, to ſeeke all meanes hee canne to make them gentle and tame, in ſo doing, yee maye ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily nouriſhe theſe kinde of birdes, or elſe not, and to haue places made fit for them to be kept in: the greateſt parte of theire feeding they prouide for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues abrode. The Pehenne doeth willinglye nouriſhe her young, as though ſhe were in bondage vnto them. They do prepare for them a ſquare court with high walles to nouriſh and feede them in, and there vſe them to the cal when they do feed them, like other poultrie. Their delight is to be alw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ies among buſhes abroad, &amp; they couer their walles, &amp; makes round aboute long galle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
<pb facs="tcp:7695:52"/>for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to walke vnder, with perches made ſquare, and mortred on the walles, and often to be made cleane. Afore three yeeres the hennes are commonly barren, and of ſmale heate, and after three yeeres they will breed well. The Cockes haue an amorous heate, as muche as the houſe cockes, and therefore they giue hym fiue or ſix hennes, for he is ready to treade the henne that comes from laying. Wherfore hee marres the egges of ſome within the henne, which are not yet already formed, &amp; hee wyll not ſuffer her to bring them to perfection, and by the anger then of that henne, the egge fales from her before they are halfe ripe: alſo at the end of winter ye muſt feede both male and females, &amp; giue them plenty of meate to make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in more heate, to giue parched beanes on the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers when they are colde, is a good feede for them, to giue to eache birde twelue ounces thereof, and to vſe it foure or fiue daies together.</p>
               <p>And alſo to feede eache by themſelues in their pennes, and to ſet faire water by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alwaies, and when ye put them abroade, let the males go with the females whyche
<pb facs="tcp:7695:53"/>will doe well, ye ſhall haue ſome Cockes ſo ſterce, that they will not ſuffer other cockes to tread their hennes. Therefore in all ſuch times it ſhall doe well to ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate them with perticions, in hotter coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treyes the pecockes doe enter into their heate, when the Eaſt windes commonlye blowes: as ſayeth <hi>Fauonius,</hi> whiche is from the xv. of February, vnto Marche or after, the ſigne when they enter into heat, is, when the Cockes doe ſpread their taile feathers, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaying is, they make a wheele. So when the hennes are troden, ye muſt looke they laye not in out places abroad, but in their houſes, and at eueninges yee muſt feele if any henne be nye to laye, or harde with egge, for in laying they will let them ſodayn fall from them, wherefore ye ſhall ſhut them vp which will laye, ſo that they lay not abrode, but in their hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, whiche muſte bee ſtrewde thicke with ſtrawe vnder their perches, to ſaue their egges when they fall from them, for as they ſitte on their pearches, ſodayne their egges falles from the hennes, and then if they light not ſofte, they breake. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore make your pearche the lower, that
<pb facs="tcp:7695:53"/>they fall not ſo farre, and their laying is in the morning, then ſearche diligentlye for to gather vp their egges, which egges will ſooner hatche being newe then bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing olde, and when ye ſet any henne, thoſe pehennes that ſit not, will laye their lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inges in the ſpring of the yeare, and thoſe that ſitte waxe ſo poore and troubled in bringing vp of hir chickens, thoſe hennes will laye no more that yere, the other that laye commonly thriſe, the firſte time ſhee will lay commonly fiue egges, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde tyme foure egges, and the thirde time ſhee will laye but three or elſe two egges.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The time beſt to ſet your pehenne. <hi>Cap. 15.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ANd when you wil ſet your henne, ye muſt ſet her with ſome henne egges withall, which ye muſt chuſe to bee fayre, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lde and great, and ſette your henne with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in the beginning of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Moone, &amp; ſet her with nine egs to ſit thereon nine days, of which egges there oughce to bee fiue Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henne
<pb facs="tcp:7695:54"/>egges, and foure henne egges, and on the tenth day, take awaye all the henne egges, and put vnder her foure other hen egges, to the end that on the thirtith day, after, in the next new Moone, all will hatche together, and when the henne doth riſe and is gone from her neaſt, yee muſte turne her Egges with your hande, and thoſe that ye turne, marke the vpper ſides thereof with ynke, that ye maye knowe which is turned when ſhe riſeth agayne, and when ſhe hath hatched let her then go wyth the young, not farre abroad before fiue &amp; thirty dayes, but tye hir by the leg with a long ſtring, and ſo keepe her in, ye muſt alſo ſee to the yong pecockes, where the damme doe loue them or not, for ſome will forſake them, and ye ſhall ſuffer no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther henne that haue yong Chickens, to come where the Pechicks are, vntill they be great, for ſhee which haue other Chic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens of hers, her nature is ſuch, ſhee will hate and forſake her owne Chickens, and loue the other, becauſe ſhee ſeeth the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chickes greater and fayrer then her own. The pehennes haue the like diſeaſe, as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:7695:54"/>poultrie haue, and are cured with the like medecines, as the rie, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ippe, and ſuch and when they are ſeuen moneths olde, ye muſt then ſee they be had to rooſt a nights with their dammes, but let them not ſitte on the bare earth, if they ſit thereon, yee ſhall ſet them on pearches as aforeſayde, to the ende they take no colde, for that will bring them to like diſeaſes as the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="52" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Of the goodneſſe of the Pecocks fleſh, and their nature in laying. <hi>Cap. 52.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>STeph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>us ſayth, that Pecockes fleſh doth nouriſh much, and are greate ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and hard to bring vp or breede. They neede no dayly tendaunce, but let y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> yong go with their dammes. They will marre Gardens and fieldes of corne, they loue a hote temperate ayre, and to breede alone in buſhes: our auncetoures didde make in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſures by theire Garde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s and houſes, with cages therein for them to go in, and
<pb facs="tcp:7695:55"/>other cloſures to nouriſh them in: but we make not ſo great matter of it, it ſhall ſuffiſe her to lodge them aboue the henne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe, and yet they loue to be at libertye, and fit on hie Trees, rather then in hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fes or places beneath, which places ought to be dayly cleane kepte, and where as they ſitte a nightes, yee ſhall often finde their egges falne from them, and after a henne hath layd and hatched, and brought forth her yong, ſhe will lay ſieldome in three yeares after, and when a Henne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginneth to laye, ſhee will ſteale from the Cocke, and laye in ſome ſecret place, then he will not ſeace to ſeeke, if hee can fynde hir, if he then find hir neaſt, he wil breake all her egges, for he hateth to ſee the yong till they haue creaſtes on their heades: a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout thyrtie dayes ſhe will hatche, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hatchte, they keepe them in the penne or neaſt with the dam, that the Cocke ſee them not, for he will then pecke and hurte them, till they haue theire creaſtes or Combes on their head, then after he will loue them well, wherefore vnto that time ye muſt keepe them well and warme, for they will ſoone be ſicke, and the moſt part
<pb facs="tcp:7695:55"/>very ſieldome liueth till they bee greate, the Cockes be hardie, and they ſaye hee ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not abide to ſee any venemous wormes, as Snakes and ſuch, but will fighte with them and kill them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="53" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The hatching and feeding of yong Pechicks. <hi>Cap. 53.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe firſte daye of their hatching, they perfume them with roſemary in a ſiue ouer coles, and then they giue them barly meale tempered with wine, and made like a thicke paſte, and ſofte Cheeſe kneaded therein, but preſſe out all the Whaye, for Whaye or cleare milke dath much annoy them, alſo ye ſhall ſometimes throw vnto them of Graſhoppers, in taking awaye their legges, and ſometime they doe giue them weuels, Sow Wormes, and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders for to cure them, for they will chiefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeeke for thoſe things, and wilde where they haunt, and if they find few thereof, after ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ckes they giue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> boyld bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as they doe the da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e, and lets them go with her, but keepe them from cold and raine, for they will ſoone pule and drawe
<pb facs="tcp:7695:56"/>their winges incontinent after by a little colde taking, ſpecially if they be not hat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched by mid Iune, in Autumne being the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but young, they will neuer endure all the winter, in hatching they turne hir egges when ſhe is from the neſt, for hir eggs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing great, ſhe cannot turne hir ſelfe: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore yee muſte then turne them with your hand as is afore declared, and marke the vpper ſides of them, elſe ye may turne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> amiſſe, and when they be hatched, giue al the pechickes to the pehenne, &amp; all the hen chickens vnto the houſe henne, but let not hir come where the pechickes are, and if ſhe ſee them, becauſe they ſhew more faire and greater then hirs, ſhee will not after loue hir owne chickens.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="54" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The ſicknes of Pehennes. <hi>Cap. 54.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>PEhennes and Peacockes are very fick when they mue their feathers, which is a kinde of chilneſſe as ſome doe ſuppoſe: then muſt ye heate the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with hony, wheat, oates, and beanes ground great, they are alſo in a great heate, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> canicular daies,
<pb facs="tcp:7695:56"/>then muſt ye giue them alwaies freſh wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter becauſe of their heate, they do giue to each cocke, v. hennes for change, for whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hir egges are but tender within hir, hee will tread her agayne, and ſo brooſe thoſe egges within her, and ſo they fall from hir and come to nought. Thus much for the gouernment of Peacockes &amp; Pehennes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="55" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The nature and feeding of Swannes. <hi>Cap. 55.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>STephanus</hi> ſaith, the haunt and feeding of Swannes, is like y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feeding of geeſe their delight is in certain places, as in ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, pooles, brookes, mixes and ſtanding pooles, and they are aſſone made tame as geeſe. They vſe commonly myres, &amp; freſh waters, but they hurt and deſtroye muche fiſhe, and ſometimes they eate of greene corne, if it be nie their haunt, as well as the tame or wilde Gooſe, to haue a coople in your ponde, or two couple for greate neede, where as many Swans are bread, there is no great ſtore of fiſhe, they treade their hennes on the water, as well as on the Lande, the hennes will make their
<pb facs="tcp:7695:57"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7695:57"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7695:58"/>neaſts themſelues, without couer. They delighte to builde on Ilandes compaſſed with water, they muſt oft be clenſed, for they file much, if they haue not ſufficiente meate, ye muſt feede them, and giue them bread ſoked in water, and certayne ſmall fiſhes, for theſe fowle are gluttons and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueners of meate, and therefore they muſt often be fedde. They lay and ſit but once a yeare, and moſt commonlye they laye but three egges, excepte they like the place, and be well fedde withall, then they will haue fiue, ſome ſeuen, and ſome nyne yong ſynets, but that is ſieldome ſeene. When they chooſe their makes they will lightly not chaunge, ſo long as hoth doe liue, and if ſome other Cocke Swanne doe chaunce to treade his henne, he wil knowe it, and then he will neuer leaue him, till hee haue kilde him that hath done it: and the Cock ſittes when the henne is gone to feede.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="56" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:7695:58"/>
               <head>¶ The nouriſhing and fatting of Swannes. <hi>Cap. 56.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THey vſe to fatte Swannes, both in open Courtes, and in houſes, and they giue them ſuch meate as they doe in fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Geeſe, as ſoked bread, fod barlye, grounde beanes, with Otes, al poulſe, and ſuch like: they chiefelye doe loue moyſte meates, and thus may ye fat them in ſix or eyght weekes, in often chaunging their meate, and clenſing their places, for they doe file much: The fleſh of old Swannes ingendereth euill iuyce, and increaceth Melancholy. Thus much of Swannes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="57" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The order and profite of Pigeons, and place for them. <hi>Cap. 57.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>STephanus</hi> ſayth, the profite in nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing pegins, is no leſſe then the profite of poultrie, ſpeciallye where they breede manye and often, and where the ſale for them is good, in ſome places they haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken at one flighte two or three hundereth
<pb facs="tcp:7695:59"/>payre of yong Pegions to ſell, and beſtow other wayes, and theſe foule neede not ſo much loking to as other fowle, trew it is, they are great eaters &amp; deuourers of corue in fieldes, and therefore it is not permitted or thought good for moſt men to build the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Douehouſes from the earth, but where there is much erable grounde of theires in thoſe fieldes nye therevnto.</p>
               <p>Let vs then for the eaſement of the far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer haue a Douehouſe from the grounde made and ſet in a place meete and hye for it, by his houſe, or ouer his houſe in a tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, or Touret of ſtone or claye, and placed very nye ſome water, becauſe a Pegion is a hote byrde, and doe heate the meate they haue taken to giue their yong, therefore they rquire water, alſo it is certayne the Pye, and the ſparrow, as well the Males as the Females, doe couer theire Egges when the henne is gone to feede, the cocks doe ſit in the meane tyme on their egges, thus they vſe to couer, till the yong be out of their ſhelles, ſo doth not the mule doues therefore it is not ſo much to be regarded, whether the Douehouſe bee open or not, but places for them to come and go, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to
<pb facs="tcp:7695:59"/>make a windowe towarde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the ſouthſide, in ſommer for them to ſleepe in, &amp; in win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to giue heat into the pegiouhouſe, and make your houſe ſure at the foundation, and wel plaſtered within, and with ſmooth ſtone couched cloſe in the bottom, for feare of their dongue do not corrrupt the place which muſt be fayre and euen within, and the chapts and holes alway ſeene too, and ſtopt cloſe for feare of Weeſels, polecats, rattes and miſe, for theſe doe commonlye happen in douehouſes which are not well ſeene to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ye ſhall dreſſe your Douchouſe without, cloſe made, for in Creuiſſes and crackes, vermine will ſeeke to enter, and ſo will deuoure both olde and yong doues, for the like daunger is in a douehouſe, as in a henhouſe, therefore ye ſhall make two centers, about your doue houſe withoute, like battelmentes of ſtone, borde or leade, one in the midſt of the wall without, and another vnder the windde or eaues, where as the Doues may enter, or ſit and proine them thereon. Some doe nayle plates of leade all aboute the windowe vnto the walles, and they make as it were a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cullis ſetnye with laths together, whiche
<pb facs="tcp:7695:60"/>maye be drawne vp euening and morning for daunger of bats, owles, and Cats, and on the toppe of the couer or louer, they make the figure of a Doue, to draw other flying by to come there, ye may alſo place ſparrow p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ts all aboute your Douehouſe without, and hang fagots of thornes by, but alwayes ſee to your Douehouſe, that none of theſe euill vermine aforeſayde d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e haunt your houſe, for they will feare the old, and deuour the yong.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="58" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ To repleniſh your Douehouſe, and to chooſe the beſt breeders. <hi>Cap. 58.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AT the beginning for to furniſh your douehouſe with yong Doues, it ſhall bee thought ſufficient to haue xx. payre of yong pegions with feathers, but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming forth, for thoſe are beſt: to haue old doues it is a daunger, for they wil retourn home agayne to their fyrſt companye, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ſuch a care they haue, or elſe to ſom other company. Among the cheefeſt bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders it is good to haue the aſhe colour, the brown, &amp; the black pegion, alſo the greſild
<pb facs="tcp:7695:60"/>with a copte heade, and the ruſſet coloure, and thoſe which are gilded about y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> necks, and thoſe whiche haue red eyne, and redde feete, are moſt frankeſt and beſt breeders, and cheefeſt repleniſhers of houſes, the whice pegion is not ſo good a breeder, and ſhe is ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ue farre off, and thereby moſte in daunger of Kites, Bozardes, Ringtayles, Dwles, and Haukes. The darke yellow, or dun Pegion, and the red and tawny co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour they breede fieldome, but to ſerue for the Kitchin, and make them tame, ye ſhall giue them firſt mil wheate, and then fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>en Comine, for theſe graynes will make them loue the houſe much, and ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>giue them the gurgions of ſifted whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Les them not go forth of the houſe of fiforene wayes after ye haue taken them and when ye giue them leaue to go forth, let it be cowaides the euening, or in a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> or ray <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ie time, to the end they may trourn, and not tar ay long forth of the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>chonſe.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7695:61"/>
            </div>
            <div n="59" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Times to feede them, and to mayne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine your broode. <hi>Cap. 59.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TRue it is, that Pegions are more cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to the Farmer in Winter, then in Sommer, or in times of froſt and ſnow or when the wheat is not bloſſommed, for then they can finde nothing in the fieldes but bents and cadlocke ſeedes, wherefore there is a charge about two monthes and more then to giue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> meate, once or twiſe a daye ye ſhall doe well, in this time you muſt let your firſte broode flie, to repleniſh your houſe all the yeare after, which time they call from Marche to into Aprill, for thoſe yong Pegions then bredde, will bee the fatteſt and tendereſt Dou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of al their broodes for thue yeare.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Columella</hi> fayth, after this order yee muſte feede both Culuers and houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doues, and becauſe of ſuch great profite by them, I will here (ſayth hee) ſay little, but cheefelye it pertaynes to a good Farmer, to haue theſe ſort of Fowle, becauſe there is ſmall charge to feede them in open we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for then they will flye abrode farre
<pb facs="tcp:7695:61"/>from the houſe, to ſeeke eche corner of the field for meate, and ſoone returne agayne, yet notwithſtanding for two or three mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths they muſt be fedde as is aforeſayde for ſo ſhall ye better maintayne and ſaue them, and being nye villages and greate townes, is daungerous for taking with nettes, and killing diuers other wayes, therefore in ſuch times the beſt is, to feede them in the Doue houſe at noone, for then is the beſt time.</p>
               <p>Alſo flower not your Doue houſe with earth, for that is to cold in Winter, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they will not like ſo well to feede ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it is beſt therefore to feede them on hye places, with windowes towarde the South, and the walles within made with holes one aboue another. Like your hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe with pertitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of lath, lome or bord, for them to breede in, or in pottes of earth faſtned againſt boords, for them to go and come at pleaſure, and alſo your houſe and holes ought to be made white, for that co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour pleaſeth them well, and ſee alwayes to keepe your Douehouſe cleane, as afore is ſayd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="60" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:7695:62"/>
               <head>¶ Of the meate and drinke for pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions and flying abrode. <hi>Cap. 60.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>COlumella</hi> ſayth, when Pegions <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> flie together about your houſe, it doeth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyte them, and ſoone they returne againe to their yo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, their water ought to be like as for your hennes, not ſo as they may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in deepe, but ſhallow for them to bathe in, for feare of chilling their egges, nor to cbuer their eggs, nor to couer their yong, alſo ye ſhall giue them meate beſide the Douehoſe without, in ſome cleane place where there is no dongue. The beſt grain for them is fceehes, orobe, eares, milwheat and cockle ſeede, and the rubbis yee caſt out of wheate, and ſuch thing as yee nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhe hennes, yee muſte often clenſe and ſweepe your Douehouſe, for the cleauer it is kept, the better they like thereof, and where they are ſo kept, they will loue that houſe the better, and hate all other whiche are foule kept, and if they be able, they will flie awaye, and come no more there, which haue bene often ſeene and prooued
<pb facs="tcp:7695:62"/>and to remedy the ſame, there is an olde conunaimdement of <hi>Democritus,</hi> whiche ſayth: Take the young of a byrde called buſe, which buildes with clay and durte, conunonly vnder battlementes, put eache one of them in earthe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pots by themſelues. Then couer and ſtop the pottes cloſe with playſter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and ſo hang them in corners of the Douehouſe, and that will make them loue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doue houſe ſo, that they wil neuer forſake it.</p>
               <p>Alſo if ye wil haue Pegions to breede, let them not be olde, nor yet too yong, and kepe thoſe which hath large bodies, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ye muſt not ſeperate them before they haue brought forth their yong, and where ſo many are fedde together they are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly finall of body, if they ioyne with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther flightes, or with ſome other kynde, the yong Pegions doe fat beſt vnder their dammes, and when they are ſomewhat ſtrong ready to flie, ſome pluckes their fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, ſome breakes their legges, ſo that they ſhall not depart from the houſe, but then yee muſt feede well their dams that they may nouriſh well their yong, and ſome doth bynde their legges, for if they breake them, as ſome ſuppoſe, it will bee
<pb facs="tcp:7695:63"/>painefull, and thereby they will waxe Ieane, wherein they ſay it is not beſt to fat them, and againe to binde their legges, they will ſtrugle, and ſo torment themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, that will hinder alſo their fatting, therefore to breake their legges, theire paine is no more but for two or three days at the muſt, and it taketh away all hope of going out, or flying abrode.</p>
               <p>Alſo to feede Pegions, take the ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mme that comes of ſeething bryne, and the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall of dregges of the bryne tubbe, &amp; then take lome drye and put them togeather, &amp; worke it like a morter, then put thereto olde chamber lye, and ſo make thereof Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, and lay them in your douehouſe on a boorde, and the pegions will gladlye feede thereon, and ſo ſhall ye haue them loue the douehouſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better, alſo if ye mixe it with Comen ſeede, wilde tares, or cockle ſeede, it wil be the better, and they will haue a more loue vnto the houſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="61" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:7695:63"/>
               <head>¶ How to perfume your Douehouſe, to cauſe them to breede and to loue it. <hi>Cap. 61.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>STephanus</hi> ſayth: if ye often perfume your douehouſe with Genoper or Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary, and ſometimes with a little fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenſence, or with ſome Lauender, theſe will make them to loue the Douehouſe more then any other, and thoſe Doues which ye haue made tame, when they doe begin to breede, yee muſt then giue them libertie, and caſt along by the wals ſmall grain or ſeedes, or where they vſe to bathe them, and ſo they will bring manye other vnto them, beſide your twentie payre that ye firſte put in, that within fortie days ye maye haue two or three times ſo manye more, for they breede three times in a yere and the good breeders foure times a yere, and there is no great care for them, but to keepe your douehouſe cleane, and clenſe the neaſtes of the olde and yong, to keepe them from fleas and lyde, and other Verinine, more needefull in Sommer then in winter.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7695:64"/>
            </div>
            <div n="62" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Pegions ſeeking their meate farre, are raueners of corne. <hi>Cap. 62.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>COlumella</hi> ſayth, Pegions are greate raueners, and farre fliars to ſeeke meat, commonly foure or ſixe miles, ſometimes ten myles, yea ſome doe ſuppoſe they will ſeeke fortie miles, and come agayne at nighte, which thing I ſcantly credite, yet ſurelye they are ſtrong and ſwifte fowle of flighte, and wil continue long in the ayre, agayne, ſome doe ſay, put a payre of doues in a houſe, and let them lacke no meat nor water, and they will deuoure a quarter of wheate, and a Tonne of water in one yeare, therefore they are calde rauening byrdes, deuourers of Corne, and reapers in fieldes, viziters of reekes, glenars of ſheaues, and theeues in Barnes, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding if ye will not ſo mayntayne your douehouſe, ye muſt let flie the firſt breede, (as is afore ſayde) in Marche and Aprll becauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thorow many occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in a yere many kill your olde doues, and by that meanes your Douehouſe is repleniſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="63" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:7695:64"/>
               <head>¶ To draw Pegions to your Doue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe. <hi>Cap. 63.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SOme doe teache, take and roſt a ſpayde bitche, take forth her guts, and fill her belly with Commine ſeede, mixte with baye ſault, and when ſhe is well and drye roſted, let her be colde, then lay her in the midſt of your Douehouſe, on a hye boorde and ye ſhall ſee the Doues will eate of her gladly, and ſo manye other Doues that ſmelles them whiche haue eaten thereof, they will come to the Douehouſe wyth them.</p>
               <p>Agayne to make a paſte or ſtimie mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to cauſe Pegions to reſorte to your Douehouſe, which is? Take ſo much as ye thinke good of a gumme whiche the <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talians</hi> cal <hi>Sorgo,</hi> or <hi>Meige,</hi> which grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth as hie as Parſenippes, or Commine, and it beareth a bigger ſeede, boyle of the ſayde gumme in Commine water, and when it hath ſodde and is flimie like buck lie, ye ſhall put therto a quantity of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, and ſome honye, and then giue it a boyle or two more, and ſtir it alwayes for
<pb facs="tcp:7695:65"/>burning too. Take of this being all hote, and annoynt the holes of your Douehouſe therewith, ſo that the pegions in going in and out, may rubbe their feete and legges thereon (which ſent will dure for certayne dayes after) and ſo many other as do ſmell the ſame, will followe them to the houſe, and after they will not depart fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thence, alſo to laye in your Douehouſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtalkes of Lauender cutte a ſhaftment long, the Doues will gather them to build theire neaſtes, and thereby will ſmell thereof, which will cauſe other Doues (ſo manye as do ſmel them) come to their douehouſe, and for the like ſome to take of ſand ſtones (which is a ſoft greete) and boyles of them in brine to ſoke, and then layes them on a table in the Douehouſe, and the Pegions will feede thereon, ſome pours on the ſaid ſtones the ſcumme that comes of boylde brine, which the Doues will like well, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doe vſe to laye on a boorde of faulte ſtones, which the Pegions will feede on, and it wil cauſe them not to ſeeke farre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broade, others do vſe to ſoke of ſoft bricks, in bryne, and then layes them on a boorde in the douehouſe, and Pegions will feede
<pb facs="tcp:7695:65"/>theron, al theſe are thought good to train doues to the houſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="64" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The nature and profite of wood pegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Culuers, and rough footed doues. <hi>Cap. 64.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>COlumella</hi> ſayth, the Wood Pegion is ſoone perceiued from other doues, they are not ſo fruitefull to lay as hennes, and yet more profitable, for they will haue yong viii. times a yere, and if the females be gnod nourſes, the young will not bee leane, and if they be faire, leane or barrain ye may fatte them like hennes, and ſell them, in like manner ye may fat Woode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culuers, but they are more rauenars and eaters then the other, and verye harde to make tame, if they be olde, they loue ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked bread in wine, and that will ſoone fat them, but ye muſt not forget to lay of gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell for them to baſke in, the Woodeuluer loues in winter to eat of yuie berries, and they lone to breede on low Trees, &amp; will haue but two yong at once.</p>
               <p>The rough footed Doue, as ſome iudge, comes of the wylde kynd, and yet they are
<pb facs="tcp:7695:66"/>to be made as tame as hennes, they are great eaters, and are very hote of nature, they lay and bring forth yong viii. or ten times a yeare, if they be well fedde. They wil neuer haue paſſing two yong at once, or one alone, and as ſoone as the henne hath hatched, ſhe will ſuffer to be toden a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne of the Cock, they are louing birdes one to another, and the Cock will ſitte on the egs while the henne feedeth abroade, and hee will feede the henne in ſitting (as the Rookes doe) and alſo he will feede the yong pegions.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="65" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Howe to take Owles that haunt your Douchouſes. <hi>Cap. 65.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>OUles that haunt your Douehouſe by night, they deſtroy many Doues both olde and yong. To take them, ſome do ſet a ladder to the roofe of the houſe afore the ſunne goe downe, and ſomewhat darke, they tye on both ſides of the roofe, a deade doue, and layes their bellies vpward, and doe ſticke lime roddes in claye round<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout them, or limde ſtrawes, and thereby takes them, and ſome ties a liue Pegion a
<pb facs="tcp:7695:66"/>pretye waye of the houſe on the grounde, and ſtickes lyme rods rounde aboute her, or prick ſtickes halfe a yearde hye from the grounde, and puts ſmall packthreede limed in the clouen toppes of the roddes, other takes them in wedging a mouſe tayle in the hole of a boord, and layes that on the ground, or ties a bird with a ſtring on the ground, and pricks lime rods about hir, and ſo takes them, in a lighte Moone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhine night, in a darke night they lay for the owle in the owle flight, for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is beſt ſetting for them: if ſhe enter into the houſe ſhe kilth all ſhe can, both olde and yong, and will remayne there, for ſhee cannot get forth agayne at the Louer, and ſhee will commonly feede of the forepart, the necke and the ſhoulders, by that ye maye know it is an Owle, and ſhe will be and ſit all day in one of the holes. Thus much for the taking of the Owle, there is alſo calles to make them come to the place in treading time, but I haue not the practiſe thereof, therefore here I will leaue with it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="66" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:7695:67"/>
               <head>¶ For Polecats and Weazels that haunt your Douehouſe. <hi>Cap. 66.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF Vermine haunt your Douehouſe, as Fechons, kenes, Polecats, Weazels and ſuch, ye muſt marke the holes where they get in to your Douehouſe. There ye ſhall ſet a whiche or fall of foure foote long, cloſe by the Douehouſe ſide, then ye ſhall hedge it ſo that nothing ſhall paſſe any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther waye, but if your Whiche or fall bee ſtaynde in taking or ſcaping of any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they will not come to the bayte within on the burge, which ye ſhall bayt with a new conye liner, or ſuch like, if that ſerue not then ſet your fall in ſome other place, or there, and hedge it, and couer it with thor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, that they may paſſe no other way but thorow the fall, and after any is taken y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> muſt clenſe and ayre your fal or Whitch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> if this ſerue not, ye ſhall put the pouder o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Arſenike into the ſlits of liuers, and tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> will poyſon them, but ſee that no othe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thing come there to eate it, before ye tak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it vp, and thus ye maye deſtroye them i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhort ſpace, if ye keepe the outſides ſmoot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7695:67"/>that no Weaſill climbe vp into the houſe, from time to time. Other wayes there is by ſetting pottes in the grounde, wyth bayte in them, and with a fall, like a pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="67" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ To take Bozardes and ſtares, that moleſt your Douehouſe. <hi>Cap. 67.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Bozarde, and Puttock, that haunt your Douehouſe, will ſodayne ſtrike at your Doues ſitting on the houſe, and ſo killes many, when any ſuch doe haunte your Douehouſe, ye ſhall ſet ſtales of liue Doues on the ground with limed ſtraws, or tye a liue mouſe and wedge her tayle into a ſtick compaſſed with three graynes or twigges lymbde, then laye it on the grounde a pretye way of the Douehouſe, and watche it, and ye ſhall ſee her ſtrike at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t, and ſo be taken, and likewiſe ſet limde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>traws about your douehouſe on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ground <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r ſmall timde twigges, thus yee maye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ake them in the ſpring. Againe, Stares <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ill commonly haunt a douehouſe in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inter time chiefely: which do moleſt the
<pb facs="tcp:7695:68"/>doues in driuing them from place to place and beating them out of their holes, and if it be colde, they will couet to ſitte vnder the Doues Winges, and being hote of nature themſelues, will make the doues ſo hote, that thereby they will become lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, and they will haue drye ſpottes on them like pockes, therefore when you ſee Stares haunt your Douehouſe, in the night ye ſhall couer the louer that no Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion go out, and then go in with a Lant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horne, for they will flie to the light, and ſo with clapnets ye may take them, and they will kill the yong, and alſo ſuck y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Doues egges.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="68" type="chapter">
               <head>How to Cock your Douehouſe. <hi>Cap. 68.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SOme ſayth, if a Douehouſe do remayn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fiue or ſixe yeare withoute taking the old cocks, they wil not proſper nor breed, becauſe of ſo many old Cocks aliue, which cannot treade themſelues, nor yet wil ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the yong Cockes to treade their hens. Therefore ſome doe couer the louer, and in a winters night goeth in with a candle and lanthorne, and with a buſh net take<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7695:68"/>all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> comes, and puts the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in baſkets, and ſo chuſe out al the old Cocks, and kils the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and lets the reſt remayne, which old cocks ye ſhal know by their gret bodies &amp; heads for they are bigger then the yonger, and they will haue a ring of blew whitiſh fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers about their neckes, and the young cocks will haue none: Agayne, ſome do ſet a ladder before night to the louer, and in the nighte one or two goeth vp the ladder with a lanthorn and light, and couers the louer hole with a net, and ſets the light by the Louer, then one knockes at the doore beneath, or elſe goeth in, then wil y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doues come to the light, and euer as they come, take the olde Cockes and kill them, but this waye (as ſome iudge) is not ſo good as the other, for they will bruſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues in flying agaynſte the poſtes and walles, in the darke houſe, and ſome do holde opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyon to lette them alone is beſt, withoute taking the olde Cookes, for I haue harde ſome ſaye, that after their Cocking their Douehouſe haue not beene ſo proſperous as before, Wherein here ye may chuſe whiche waye beſt to take. Thus much for the cocking your douehouſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="69" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:7695:69"/>
               <head>¶ Of Pegion dongue. <hi>Cap. 69.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe nature and propertye of Pegion dongue is to heate the earth, therfore keepe wel their dongue ye take out of the Pegion houſe, and meddle it when ye liſt with cowe dongue, or other horſe dongue, and it doth more then Sheepe dongue, for Pegion dongue is very hote, whiche will ſerue to amende colde and naked places, in your fieldes or medowes, and alſo to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhe and ſucker olde trees agaynſt colde and weat.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="70" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Of Turtle Doues. <hi>Cap. 70.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>COlumella</hi> ſayth, to nouriſhe Turtles for profite, it is ſuperfluons, for they will laye no egges in your Cages nor hatche yong, therefore from the time you haue taken them, they keepe them to fatte more ſooner then manye other Byrds, but not in all times of the yeare a like, for in winter there is great care to fatte them, and in this time there is more plenty, and the price doeth diminiſhe, in Sommer
<pb facs="tcp:7695:69"/>they will fatte themſelues if they haue meate to eate, there is no other payn but to feede them with mil wheat, not becauſe they will not fatte with other wheate, but becauſe they loue myl wheate better, and yet in Winter they are as ſoone made fat (as Woode Culuers) with ſops of breade ſoked in Wyne, and like with other thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and they do not entreate them like o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Pegions, in holes, but ſtones ſette in the walles, not with partitions, but as ſtayes for them to ſit on, they muſt be clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with nettes rounde, that they flie not forth, and thus they vſe to fat them with mil wheate, and other wheate which muſt be giuen drye, halfe a buſhell a daye is y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for ſixe ſcore Turtles and alwayes they muſt haue freſhe water in clean veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, and ſee that their dongue marre not their feete, which donge is good to keepe for the fatting of trees, as all other byrdes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aue thoſe that ſwim, and to fatte theſe, ye muſt chuſe the yongeſt rather then the ol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſt, alſo about harueſt, the yong Turtles <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re big ynough to fat, then they vſe to fat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hem.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Stephanus</hi> ſayth, thoſe fowle are ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:7695:70"/>to be nouriſhed then to breede. They are vſed as Fezantes, with braunches ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed to the wales, and faſtned wiar, with doores hard by, alſo in the corners ye ſhal make places for them to pearche on, and ſet braunches of Genoper and Bayes, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout your trees ſet agaynſte the walles, alſo yee ſhall faſten ſmall pannyers to the walles, to tyce them to laye, if they haue any deſire thereto.</p>
               <p>And yee ſhall place your couer for your cage the height of a man, and places made rounde for them to rooſte vnder, &amp; ſtrawde with freſh ſtraw, renewing it often, and make places for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to eat, with troughes for them to drinke in, and chaunge it ofte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> They loue the hote ayre, in colde tymes they paſſe the Seas in flockes, from on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> countrey to another, they are made tam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as our houſe poultrie, which is very har<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to doe, for they are not to be fedde, but fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the delicateneſſe of them in feaſtes &amp; ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quets. The Turtle is more eaſie to mak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> tame, then other Quayles or Partrich<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and to fat alſo if they be taken yong, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by giuing them wine, they make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get their libertie, for they will bee very
<pb facs="tcp:7695:70"/>angry when they are firſte take, and they neuer laye incloſed, nor fat ſcantly in win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, they are contrary to other foule, as Geues and ſuch, their nouriſhment is fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, barly and moſte of other grayne, ye ſhall giue freſhe water in a veſſell, ſo they may bathe therein, and lay by of grauilye ſende to ſcower and heale them, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they are ſicke, and looke to their billes for the pippe, and take it away if there be anye, alſo looke to their feet for troubling with their dongue, and alſo vnder their wings, if they haue any vermine, yee muſt helpe them as you doe your poultrie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="71" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The ordering and fatting of hearnes. <hi>Cap. 71.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>STephanus</hi> ſayth, I haue afore reſited of the great curioſitie of diuerſe kinds of fowles to nouriſh, and here agayne I muſt faye the like of the hearne, for ſhee is but expenſe, without profite to any. True it is, for princes and great Lords, to tame to flye for pleaſure, otherwiſe the Hearne alone, it is but the daintie mouth to eate the fleſh, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaying of ſome is, the hearne is a royall meate, but this pleaſure coſts
<pb facs="tcp:7695:71"/>double charge, for ſhee is a greate ſpoyler and deuourer of fiſhe, we may think them the father of a familye in houſholde, be it Prince or great Lord will ſometyme take pleaſure in the flight of the hearne, or for his mouth, there is no other reaſon to bee made, then for to make a place to keepe them in, noc onelye for pleaſure, but alſo profice for his Lorde or mayſter, nowe to make this place to fatte them and keepe them in bondage, which loues dayly to be abrode alone, and ſolitarye in their mynd, and yet not reſt long in a place, excepte it pleaſe them well, for ſhee is waywarde, fearefull, and delights to builde on hyghe Trees, a place for them may well be made for two occaſions, one to nouriſhe them in for the pleaſure of the Prince, and agayne to haue them ready at neede for anye ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet, and thoſe that are ſo cloſed, will call others that flie by, and cauſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to breede there abouts.</p>
               <p>Alſo ye muſt conſider of the place meete for them, to keepe them in, for if it rayne not there ſometime, ſhe wil take no plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure therein, nor yet breede, but mourne, and ſo pyne and die, alſo ye muſt houe a
<pb facs="tcp:7695:71"/>running water thorowe the midſt of your courte or place, for the Hearn is a watriſh Fowle, and hath pleaſure for to looke for fiſhe in waters, to take Eeles and other ſmall fiſhe. The place for them oughte to be couered all ouer with lathes, ſet nye to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and walde or boorded rounde, ſixe foote hye, ſo that other Hearnes if they will may make their neaſtes thereon, and their feeding ſhall be liue Eeles, or cutte, and caſt in water, and to giue other ſmall fiſhe, ſometimes the entrailes and liuers of beaſtes cutte ſmall, or dogges fleſhe cut and giuen them, to fatte for flighte or ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet, they will not lightly breede beeing in bondage, they be a pleaſure for flying, but not to let flye nie their Court, for the reſt will be afrayde, and thoſe that come there to breede they will forſake the place and build there no more.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="72" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The ordering and nouriſhing of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tridges. <hi>Cap. 72.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Partridge is a dayntie Byrd, and liues in fleldes among buſhes and hed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, the Cockes are ſtoute and hote of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb facs="tcp:7695:72"/>and the hennes alſo, and will laye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue twentie egges at a time, and bring foorth their yong, they breede but once a yeare, which is in the ſpring, the Cockes will fight for their hennes, and he whiche hath the victory will conſtrayne the other Cocke to follow him and run after him, as doth the henne, their feeding is very dain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with millet wheat, or of pannick wheat or other wheate, alſo if ye take the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tridge egges and ſet them vnder a henne that ſitteth, ſhe will hatch them and bring them forth and nouriſhe them like houſe chickens, they muſt bee fedde with antes egges, till they be of a more ſtrength, and of a good bigneſſe, then ye may feede them as ye doe houſe chickens, and thoſe which ye ſo nouriſhe and feede, yee maye eaſilye keepe them tame in your Courtes, and they will breede from tyme to tyme, and nouriſhe their yong, if ye helpe them with antes egges, whyle they are young, and ye muſt make pretye places on the ground for them to breede in, and couered with boughes, for they loue commonlye not to be ſeene or haue any to looke and beholde them, ye muſt gyue them of freſhe water,
<pb facs="tcp:7695:72"/>ſhorning and euening, &amp; keepe their court cleane.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="73" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Quayles feeding and their nature. <hi>Cap. 73.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Quayles are a dayntie fleſhe vſed for banquets, they are of nature furious fighters, and curriſhe, therefore they that keepe them, let not them haue ſo much li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertye as other Fowles haue, nor yet ſo muche light, therefore they couer theire cages with canuas, or leather, for moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and buſiyng their wings agaynſt the ſides of the Cage, they put their meat and drinke in veſſels a part, eache Quayle by himſelfe, whiche will make them ſooner to fatte, they loue to eate greene wheate, and alſo of other wheate, whiche is theyr principall meate. They vſe muche that circuite where they are commonlye bred, they breede in Corne fieldes, and in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures, they will haue fiue or ſixe at a time and breede but once a yeare, they loue the place whereas there groweth muche elle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borye, called neeſing powder, of ſome: whereof <hi>Didimus</hi> ſayth, their fleſh is lax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atiue, and alſo will make ones head heauy
<pb facs="tcp:7695:73"/>and alſo will make ones heade heauy and euill, and for this cauſe ſome doe ſear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> them with Wheate, and boyles them wel therewith, if any find greefe thereby, they drinke the decoction that millet is ſodd in or the ſeede of Myrre, which is good alſo to giue Quayles to eate, the yong loues to be feeding among graſſe, to be picking on flies and ſuch. The tame yee maye vſe them to a call, as ye doe your chicken.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="74" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The Gulles how to feede. <hi>Cap. 74.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>GUlles doe breede in the rockes, and bankes of the Sea, in extreame cold weather they flye from the Sea into the Lande, and liues on mountaynes and playnes, and they feede there on wormes and ſuche as they canne get, and they that doe fatte them doe take them readie to fly, in holes and rockes by the Sea ſyde, and then they feede them, the old are not good to fatte, they feede both with fiſhe &amp; fleſhe, as the liuers of beaſtes, and freſh ſea fiſhe as place and ſuch, cutte in ſmal peeces and giuen them, their veſſels of water oughte
<pb facs="tcp:7695:73"/>to be pannes of earth, filde with fayre wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, then lay therein brick battes or ſtones that they bathe not therein, for they will deſyre to bathe, and that will keepe them leane, their meate muſt be chopte rewe, and layde on boordes, and they commonly fighte (and crye) one with another, and they be great rauenars, and oughte to be fedde twiſe or thriſe a daye with ſweete meate, and they vſe to laye it in fayre wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to keepe it ſweete two or three dayes, they breede but once a yere, and will haue foure or fiue in a neaſt, or more.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="75" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Of Puets. <hi>Cap. 75.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>PUets are byrdes or fowle that breedes in Rocks and bankes by the Sea, they are taken young from the neaſtes like the Gulles, and fedde for banquets, they are a dayntie fleſhe, and pleaſaunte to eate. They are kepte to fatte in large houſes and courtes, for ſome doe vſe to put them in parts, for they will fight like y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gulles, one with another, and thoſe that they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende to eate ſhortlye, they feede them a parte with curdes, for that will ſoone fat
<pb facs="tcp:7695:74"/>them, and make their fleſh whyte, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>te, and fayre, ſo will not thoſe fed with fleſh, as lyuers of Oxen and ſheep, ſmally chopt as is aforeſaid of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gulles &amp; layd on fayre boords twiſe a day, for they are rauenars, &amp; to giue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fayre water laid with ſtones like as ye do for Gulles aforeſayd, for ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing wil kepe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lean, &amp; they breede but once a yere, &amp; haue 5 or 6 at a time, or me.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="76" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Of Feſantes and their nature. <hi>Ca. 76.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>STephanus</hi> ſayth, it is a great curioſitie to nouriſhe the olde Feſants which <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumella</hi> doth name them hens of <hi>Numidie</hi> but for thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> may feede them, it is both pleaſure and profite, but ye muſt haue one to doe no other thing, for they require great attendaunce, &amp; yee muſt make their Court ſomewhat hye, ſet alſo with bordes agaynſte the walles, round about y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> court in length, &amp; their pearche made ſo to ſitte where the ſunne may ſhine, and each byrd his place, and alſo to haue one generall houſe to clenſe the hens, and to giue them meate, and cloſed all aboue, &amp; before with laths very nie together, about the height of a pole from the earth well couerd all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, alſo the Feſante Cockes and hennes,
<pb facs="tcp:7695:74"/>are byrds of a ſtoute courage, and are not content to be encloſed or made tame, if they bee aboue a yeare olde, and the olde hennes are greeued, and diſdayneth to lay or ſit, and the yong wil not ſo ſoone agree with the ayre, being ſo conſtrayned there: becauſe it is not lyke the Region from whence they were take, alſo there muſt be giuen to one male two females, the Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>males laye but once a yere and ſhe begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in Marche, and layth ſome twentye egges by order, or ſhe ſtint, and then ſhee ſits on all together, or ye may giue xv. of hits, and the reſt of other ſtraunge egges <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f ye will, ſhe ſittes thyrtye dayes, and in ſetting them yee muſt haue the lyke dilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>euce as of your houſe hennes, and theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſt not bee without their houſes, and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ong being once hatched, ſhal haue a mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ure made of ſodde barlye branne, then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>olde and giuen, and to giue them wheat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eale, the whiche yee ſhall ſometymes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ire together and ſo giuen, ſometimes of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>raſhappers, and the egges of Ants, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ten to change their water to haue it ſtill <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eane, for they are ſubiecte vnto the like ſeaſes as the houſe hennes are.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="77" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:7695:75"/>
               <head>¶ How to fat Fezantes. <hi>Cap. 77.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe auncientes did vſe to fat and nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhe the Feſantes, both Cockes and hennes not onelye for increaſe, but as we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for feaſts and banquets, and in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning they giue them water and wine mix together, to make them forget their natu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> rall place and then they feede them wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> barlie meale ſteeped in water, and groun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> beanes, and ſtieped barlye mixte togethe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with millet, and alſo naues and linſeed boylde, then dryde, and mixte with barly meale, and likewiſe to heate them and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> purge them, they did vſe to giue them f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nigreke the ſpace of fiue dayes, and ſo th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> were clenſed and mude in forty dayes, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thus ſome keepes them that are of ſkil, nouriſhing of daintie Fowle, and <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mella</hi> ſayth, ye may well giue them me to fat them for banquets, for few or no being wylde hennes are giuen to lay or ſit being kept in bondage and bredde vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brode.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="78" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:7695:75"/>
               <head>¶ Of Godwits, Knots, and Stynts. <hi>Cap. 78.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Godwits, and Knots are taken yong, they breede in holes and Rockes by the Sea, and alſo in Ilandes nye the Sea, they are exteemed a dayntie meate, and pleaſaunt, and coſtlye to keepe, and make fatte, for they are commonlye fedde with Wheate, and fayre water other fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding I haue not knowne.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="79" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Of Plouers. <hi>Cap. 79.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THere are two kynde of Plouers, the one is called the greene Plouer, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ue cal the Lapwing, and the other is cald <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he gray Plouer which breeds in Ilands <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ye the Seas, or in great heathes, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arriſhe groundes, and alſo the greene Plouer breedes commonlye in marriſhes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eathes, Fieldes, and ſuche, they breede <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut once a yeare, and when they lay as in Harche and Aprill, they will not haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſt foure or fiue yong, their feeding is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mmonly on Wormes and flies and ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:7695:76"/>as they can get, they will hardly be made came being encloſed, for they are a wylde kinde of peuiſhe byrdes to tame. They are fedde with wheate and Water, like the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fowle aforeſayde, the yong greene Plouer is eaſter to make tame, and they vſe to kepe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in gardens to kill worines and giues them wormes and water, but then beware the Rite and the Catte, thus muche for the Plouers.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="80" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Of the Bitter and Curlew. <hi>Cap. 80.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Bitter is a ſtrange kinde of fowle, and liues commonlye in Fennes, and in moriſh heathes, they are euill to bee made tame. Their fleſhe is pleaſaunte to eate, and are kept for banquets, they are fed with raw liuers of beaſts, &amp; ſuch lyke, they are yrefull, and will ſtrike ſodaynlye at a mans face, and ſtand lurking in a cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner like the hearn, &amp; they feare the ſight o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a mans face, and thoſe that doe fat them they doe cram them with raw fleſhe cutt in ſmall peeces, which they will caſt it v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> agayne. Therfore when ye cramme then ye muſt put a double threede ouer his bil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7695:76"/>to poſſe his noſtrils, and thorow his no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrils put a ſmall ſticke or quill, and that will keepe the threed vp, and let him from caſting vppe his meate agayne, if that were not, he woulde caſt it vppe inconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent.</p>
               <p>The Curlew is a fowle that feeds com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monlye in moyſte groundes and heathes, their fleſh is pleſant to eat, they feed com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly on wormes and ſuch, and they fat them with wheate and fayre water, other feeding I know not what is beſt for them, Thus much for the Bitter &amp; the Curlew.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="81" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Of Blackburdes and Thruſtles. <hi>Ca. 81.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Blackbyrde is a dayntie fleſhe to eate, &amp; they are more charable to keepe then many others, &amp; they that ſhall keepe them in cages being taken old, &amp; brought from other countreies, they are hardly ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to be tranſported, alſo if ye put the old to be fed in cages, ſome therof wil ſodain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y die of enuy and feare, when they are ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the Fowler and put to fatte, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the beſt remedye is, ye ſhall take of came Blackbyrds and put vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wild,
<pb facs="tcp:7695:77"/>and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they are accuſtomed to be ſeruſt, the wylde in ſeeing the tame feede, they will feede alſo, and ſo forget their anger and libertie, and thus ye may beſt bring the wilde to be tame, and to receiue theyr meate with the other.</p>
               <p>Alſo their cages muſt be made toward the South, with pearches of woode ſet in the walles to ſit and proyne, when they haue eaten, and ye muſt not ſet their pear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches aboue a mans heighth, that in ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding on the ground they may touch them, ye ſhall not feede them where their Pear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches are, for keeping their meat more cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner without their dongue, and for their meate, ſome do vſe to feede them with dry figges, and barlye Flowar beaten togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and giue them thereof, ſo they may leaue ſome, alſo ſometimes they chewe it in their mouthes, and ſo giues it vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but where as many are, it is not quite coſt to feede them, and other ſome are of opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to feede and giue them of diuers kinds of meate is good, for feare if they ſhould be weary of one meate, as ſometimes t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> giue them wormes, antes, wheate, hard egges and ſoked breade in water, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7695:77"/>ſeedes of wylde tares, or Charuel ſeedes, or wylde Oliues, or yuie berryes, and wylde Apples, for when they are in the Woodes, they eate of all theſe, but in their Cages it will trouble them, and yet cauſe them to prouoke appetite, whiche is neceſſarye, for the more they eate, the ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner they will be fatte, and ye ſhall fill alſo their veſſels with mill wheate, whiche is the cheefeſt meate for their delight, the other doe ſerue but as ſauce of pleaſure, their drinke ought to be cleare water and often chaunged, and thus ye may fatte the blackebyrde, ſo may ye nouriſhe and fatte the Thruſtle, and Fieldfare, other byrdes there is, whiche are not ſo neceſſarye to be fed, nor yet ſo profitable. Thus I leaue for the gouerning and fatting of Black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byrdes and Thruſtles, with all the gouernment of poul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie and Fowle a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſayde.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7695:78"/>
            </div>
            <div n="82" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ To make white byrdes come of anye egges. <hi>Cap. 82.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke your egges of what byrd ye wil, and lay them two dayes long in honye and then put them agayn in the neaſt, and let them be ſat on, and ye ſhall haue them whyte.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="83" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ To make hens of the colour of your egges ye ſet her. <hi>Cap. 83.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>YE ſhall take ſome Egges of a broode henne, and coloure them with what colour ye will, and put them to the henne, and ye ſhall ſee the Chickens to be of the ſame colour ye coloured the egges.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="84" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ For Geeſe. <hi>Cap. 84.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF yee ſette a Gooſe where as ſhee ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> come by no water to bathe her, whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhe riſeth her egges then will not proſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> nor come to any perfection, Alſo when gooſe haue ſatte her time, and cannot w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> breake and vncloſe her egges, yee ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7695:78"/>burne the ſtalkes and leaues dride of cole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wortes before her neaſt, and perfume her neaſt therewith, and ſoone after they ſhall vncloſe and hatche, likewiſe if ye haue di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers broode Geeſe, and but one Gander, ſome Ganders will loue but one or two Geeſe and hate the reſt, therefore it ſhall be good to haue mo Ganders then one to ſerue their Goſlings, for when the Gooſe leades and goes afore her yong, the crowe will take ſome behynde hir, and therefore ye ſhall ſee the Gander come behynde his goſlinges, and thereby ſaues manye from the Crowes and Rites.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>¶ To make hennes lay.</head>
               <p>TO cauſe hennes to laye al the winter, take the croppes of nettles when they are readye to ſeede, then drie them, and mix them with bran and hempeſeede, and ſo giue it your hennes a morninges, and they will lay, yee may alſo giue them the ſeedes of Cowmake, a weede amongeſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orne ſo calde in <hi>Turnars</hi> Herball, whiche will alſo cauſe them to lay.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:7695:79"/>
               <head>¶ For breeding Capons.</head>
               <p>ANd thoſe that woulde breede manye Capons, ye muſt not then haue anye Cock that is vſed to fighte, for then hee will alway beate your Capons, and not ſuffer them to be at reſt but hunt &amp; kill them at length.</p>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="index">
            <pb facs="tcp:7695:79"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The table of all the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall</hi> matters in this Booke, following by Alphabet.</head>
            <list>
               <head>A.</head>
               <item>AGaynſte the pippe. Cap. 13,</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>B.</head>
               <item>Bytters how to make fat. 80.</item>
               <item>Blackbyrdes how to nouriſh. 81.</item>
               <item>Bozardes that haunt douehouſes. 67.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>C.</head>
               <item>Capons how to fat 25.</item>
               <item>Catarre or rewme in poultrie. 14.</item>
               <item>Caruing of poultrie. 31.</item>
               <item>Caruing yong chickens. 23.</item>
               <item>Chickens newly hatched. 7.</item>
               <item>Chickens of a later broode. 11.</item>
               <item>Chickens fed from the Dam. 12.</item>
               <item>Cocking of a Douehouſe. 68.</item>
               <item>Culuers and their nature, 64,</item>
               <item>Curlewes how to feede. 80.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:7695:80"/>
            <list>
               <head>D.</head>
               <item>Dongue of Pegions profitable. 69</item>
               <item>Ducks profitable for the huſband. 41</item>
               <item>Ducks vvild to nouriſh. 42</item>
               <item>Ducks and their nature. 42.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>E.</head>
               <item>Egges to keepe long 8.</item>
               <item>Egges how to gather and ſaue. 9</item>
               <item>Egges vvithout a Cock. 9.</item>
               <item>Egs to make vvhite byrdes. 82.</item>
               <item>Egs to haue all the vvinter, 10.</item>
               <item>Eyes enflamed of poultrie. 24.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>F.</head>
               <item>Fatting of Capons. 25.</item>
               <item>Feeding great Chickens. 28.</item>
               <item>Feeding yong poullets. 29.</item>
               <item>Feeding of poultrie. 26</item>
               <item>Fieldfares how to feede. 82</item>
               <item>Fethers of geeſe vvhich are beſt. 40.</item>
               <item>Fezants how to fat. 77</item>
               <item>Fezantes and their nature. 76.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:7695:80"/>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>luxe in poultrie to helpe. 18.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>G.</head>
               <item>Ganders vvhite are the beſt. 36.</item>
               <item>Geeſe and their gouernment. 33.</item>
               <item>Geeſe and places fit for them. 34</item>
               <item>Geeſe vvhat paſture beſt. 35.</item>
               <item>Geeſe al white are the beſt. 36.</item>
               <item>Geeſe yong how to fat. 37.</item>
               <item>Geeſe yong to fat. 38.</item>
               <item>Geeſe how many to one gander. 39.</item>
               <item>Goſlinges how to feede. 37.</item>
               <item>Godwits how to nouriſh. 78.</item>
               <item>Goulles how to nouriſh and fat. 74.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>H.</head>
               <item>Haw in the eyes of poultrie. 24</item>
               <item>Henhouſe to order and make. 1.</item>
               <item>Hens with their good properties. 4.</item>
               <item>Hens vvhen beſt to ſet them. 5.</item>
               <item>Hens yong to ſet. 6.</item>
               <item>Hens how many meete for a cock. 15</item>
               <item>Hens that vſe to hatche abrode. 16.</item>
               <item>Hennes that ſit and riſe in weate vvea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. 22.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:7695:81"/>
               <item>Heunes of the colour of the egges y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſet her. 63.</item>
               <item>Hens how to make fat. 27.</item>
               <item>Hearns to nouriſh and to fat. 71.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>K.</head>
               <item>Knots how to feede. 78.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>L.</head>
               <item>Lice &amp; varmine in poultrie. 20</item>
               <item>Letting forth poultry a mornings. 30</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>M.</head>
               <item>Meete when to feede poultrie. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>O.</head>
               <item>Ordring Poultrie a mornings. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>Owles that haunt a Douehouſe. 6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>P.</head>
               <item>Partridge how to nouriſh. 7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>Perfuming the douehouſe. 6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>Pegions to draw to the douehous. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>Pegio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s with profit &amp; place for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:7695:81"/>
               <item>Pegions to repleniſh your houſe. 58</item>
               <item>Pegeons and beſt breeders. 58</item>
               <item>Pegions to feede and maintaine. 59</item>
               <item>Pegions that fly abroad to feede. 60</item>
               <item>Pegions that ſeeke their meate farre. 62.</item>
               <item>Pegions and their nature. 64.</item>
               <item>Peacockes and the goodnes of theire fleſhe. 52.</item>
               <item>Pehens their nature in laying. 52.</item>
               <item>Pechickes hatching and feeding. 53.</item>
               <item>Pehens and their ſicknes. 54.</item>
               <item>Pegins dong good for trees. 69.</item>
               <item>Pippe the cauſe and remedy. 13.</item>
               <item>Plouers how to nouriſhe. 79.</item>
               <item>Polecats that haunt doue houſes. 66.</item>
               <item>Puets how to fatte. 75.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Q.</head>
               <item>Quailes how to nouriſhe. 73.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>R.</head>
               <item>Rough footed doues to kepe. 64.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>S.</head>
               <item>Sheldrakes to nouriſhe. 41.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:7695:82"/>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>gnes in a good Cock. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</item>
               <item>Stares that moleſt doues in their no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. 6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>Stynts how to nouriſh. 78.</item>
               <item>Stopping the flux in poultrie. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</item>
               <item>Swans nature and feeding. 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>Swans how to nouriſh and feede. 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>T.</head>
               <item>Teales how to nouriſh. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>Threſtles to fat. 8<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>Things good in keeping poultry. 32.</item>
               <item>Turquie hens and their profite. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</item>
               <item>Turquies to nouriſh. 45.</item>
               <item>Turquie cocks beſt treaders 46.</item>
               <item>Turquy he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in hatchi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g their yo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g. 47.</item>
               <item>Turquy hens the order &amp; feding. 48.</item>
               <item>Turquie chicke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s how to nouriſh. 48.</item>
               <item>Turquies the common feeding. 49.</item>
               <item>Turtle doues to nourishe. 70.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>W.</head>
               <item>VVezels that haunt a douehouſe. 66.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:7695:82"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
